<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Innovations of popery in the Church of Rome, calling for repentance and reformation; being as a wall of separation between Christians and Christians. : Wherein is shewed, that the mystery of iniquity, Sodom and Egypt spiritual ... are all founded in innovations. : Given forth partly to stir up our thankfulness to God for his former mercies to this nation ... / By one that loves all that fear the Lord ... W.T.</title>
            <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94746</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789432</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789432</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172742</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94746)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172742)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2647:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Innovations of popery in the Church of Rome, calling for repentance and reformation; being as a wall of separation between Christians and Christians. : Wherein is shewed, that the mystery of iniquity, Sodom and Egypt spiritual ... are all founded in innovations. : Given forth partly to stir up our thankfulness to God for his former mercies to this nation ... / By one that loves all that fear the Lord ... W.T.</title>
                  <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>139, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Northcott in George-Yard in Lumbard-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: [4] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Llyfrgell Genedlaethol Cymru/National Library of Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172742:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172742:1"/>
            <p>INNOVATIONS OF POPERY IN THE CHURCH of ROME, CALLING For Repentance and Reformation; being as a Wall of Separation between Chriſtians and Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed,</p>
            <p>That the Myſtery of Iniquity, <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> Spiritual, <hi>Babylon</hi> the Great, and the Mother of Harlots and Great Whore, are all founded in Innovations.</p>
            <p>Given forth partly to ſtir up our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God for his former Mercies to this Nation in delivering it from the Horrid Popiſh Thraldom and Ignorance; and for his preſerving it at this time from the impending Storm that threatned us: partly alſo to help to eſtabliſh thoſe that are wavering in their minds towards it: and to encourage thoſe that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, who truly fear God, in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of deliverance from under it.</p>
            <p>By one that Loves all that fear the Lord, and love Truth and Righteouſneſs in their Hearts, whereſoever they are found.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Northcott</hi> in <hi>George-Yard</hi> in <hi>Lumbard-Street,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172742:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172742:2"/>
            <head>INNOVATIONS OF <hi rend="blackletterType">Popery</hi> IN THE CHURCH OF ROME, CALLING For Repentance and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HHving ſome things lying fair before me concerning the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and Popery; and having a deſire to expreſs the ſame with as much
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172742:3"/>clearneſs and plainneſs as I can; it will be needful for me, in the firſt place to diſtinguiſh both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Perſons and Perſons; and alſo between Things and Things; being prompted thereunto by the manner of our Lord and Maſters writing to the ſeveral Churches in <hi>Aſia, Rev.</hi> 2. &amp; 3. He owns the Good, and diſowns the Evil, in the ſame Church, and in the ſame Perſons. He doth not own all for good, becauſe ſome things were good: Nor doth he diſown and reject all as evil, becauſe ſome things were evil. His example I deſire to follow.</p>
            <p>Now therefore concerning Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they are thus diſtinguiſhed. The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> taken in a general ſenſe, conſiſts of theſe three Parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Hierarchy, or Ruling Prieſthood, who are as the Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Teachers, and Rulers of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172742:3"/>the People, from the Pope down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in Subordination to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Inhabitants of the Earth; that is, ſuch as have their minds and hearts on the Earth, and have no power of Truth in them: but all their Religion ſtands only in their outward Form: whoſe life is in that, and Zeal for that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such as in ſincerity of Heart ſeek after the Lord, and purſue (according to their underſtanding) things that are ſpiritual or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly: who Hunger and Thirſt after Righteouſneſs; whoſe hearts are drawn after the Lord, and who love Truth in the inward parts, and hate Lying, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. Theſe, altho they may be under many miſtakes in judgment or knowledge, by reaſon of edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or outward teaching yet I look upon them as people;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172742:4"/>whom God will own; ſaying to them, <hi>Come out of her my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And concerning things, I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between thoſe ancient Truths, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had, and lived in at firſt, and ſtill retain; and thoſe Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations brought in among them afterwards.</p>
            <p>And therefore I call nothing <hi>Popery</hi> but <hi>Innovations</hi> introduced, or upheld by ſome Pope or Popes, wherewith the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is infeſted. I do not comprehend thoſe ancient Truths, which they lived in at firſt in the Apoſtles days, and which they ſtill retain, under the name of Popery: but as I ſaid, only their Innovations; ſuch as theſe which follow, and which I ſhall endeavour to detect by evidence of Scripture, and to manifeſt the Truth obſcured by them, as there is need.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Popes Exaltation, or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172742:4"/>his being made Univerſal Biſhop. This is an Innovation directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Doctrine of Chriſt, and of his Holy Apoſtles; and practice of the primitive times. Its contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, plainly expreſt in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring Teſtimony, both of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke.</hi> Read <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.25, 26. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.42, 43. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.25, 26, 27. Its in all theſe places flatly forbidden the Servants of Chriſt, to exerciſe Dominion or Authority over their Fellow Diſciples: and they are commanded, not to be like the Princes of the Nations, or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles herein. The words in <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> are theſe, <hi>Ye know that the Princes of the Gentiles</hi> (or Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) <hi>exerciſe Dominion over them, and they that are great, exerciſe Authority upon them: But it ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi> What can be ſpake more plainly and fully than
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172742:5"/>this? <hi>But it ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi> The words in <hi>Mark,</hi> and in <hi>Luke</hi> are to the ſame purpoſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting this Exaltation and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. And the Apoſtles of Chriſt they kept to this Doctrine: <hi>Paul</hi> denyed ſuch Dominion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Not that we have Dominion over your Faith, but are helpers of your joy.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> excludes this Lordſhip likewiſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Neither as being Lords over Gods Heritage, but being enſamples to the Flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, if we look at the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical State of the Churches; and take notice of the ſeveral Epiſtles of Chriſt to the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> we ſee no Superiority gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven therein to one Angel of the Churches above onother. But they are diſtinctly writ unto, as having no precedency one above another, but every one ſtanding diſtinct in his own Sphere or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172742:5"/>Charge. So that this Exaltation of the Popes is diſſonant to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Goſpel, and crept in through impurity and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in after Ages, as by and by I ſhall make appear.</p>
            <p>Only firſt take notice, that this Exaltation of the Popes is an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation very fitly ſuiting or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Myſtery of Iniquity. For <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks plainly of ſuch an exalted one in the Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <hi>Who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is Worſhipped</hi> (that is, above all Magiſtrates and Rulers who are called Gods. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1, 6.) <hi>Who hath his Seat in the Temple of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. So the Pope he hath his Exaltation in the Church or Temple of God.</p>
            <p>Now let us take notice how this Innovation of the Popes great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation over all his Fellow Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops came in. It had its riſe from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172742:6"/>Pride and Ambition: and from the Gift of a wicked Man. Pride and Ambition working in him that was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have the preheminence, he obtained of <hi>Phocas,</hi> then Emperor, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be, and ſhould be called, <hi>Caput omnium Eccleſiarum,</hi> The Head of all the Churches. And ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that he ſhould be the Head of all the Biſhops. This was the riſe of the Tranſcendent Exaltation of the Popes, or Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi> It was the Gift of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Phocas;</hi> a Man of whom it is recorded, That he was <hi>(Tyrannus, patriaque calamitas, ſub quo omnis generis mala exundaverunt)</hi> a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, the Calamity of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, under whom all manner of wickedneſs abounded. Thus you ſee what manner of Original this Innovation had: and what the Foundation of it was. And the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172742:6"/>Popes came not to this height till about ſix Hundred Years or more after the Birth of Chriſt, as Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory informs. <hi>Bucholcer</hi> pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſets down the Year 607. when <hi>Boniface</hi> 3. obtained this of <hi>Phocas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But tho the Pope was thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted among men: yet hereby he received the greater fall in the Kingdom of Chriſt, <hi>where he that humbleth himſelf as a little Child is greateſt: But he that exalts himſelf ſhall be abaſed, Matth.</hi> 18.4. &amp; <hi>Ch.</hi> 23.12. So that his Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is his fall, his earthly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation was his fall in heavenly things: here he fell from the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heavenly Station, in which Chriſt ſtated his Church. And therefore its not unworthy the Conſideration; whether that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of his was not that falling of a Star from Heaven to the Earth ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. Eſpecially if
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172742:7"/>we conſider the Concomitants or Conſequences of the fall. The Pope now having none to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trol him, but being thus exalted above all, he had power to bring in what innovations he would. As the Star fallen from Heaven to the Earth had power given him to open the bottomleſs Pit; which comes all to one. For what is that Pit? We cannot imagine it to be a Pit in the Earth, that had a Lock and Key upon it: but mans Heart is as a deep Pit, without a Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom or Foundation: and the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations thereof is as a Smoke iſſuing out of that Pit. Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are the imaginations of mans Heart; and like Smoke they darken the Sunſhine of the Goſpel, and fill the Air (that ſpiritual Air that mens Spirits ſhould breath in) with darkneſs, and unwholeſome Miſts. And this the Pope had power to do when he was exalted;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172742:7"/>and the Star had power to do when he was fallen. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this his Exaltation was his fall. And if he was a Star as the Angels of the Churches were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; this his exaltation ſeems plainly to be the falling of that Star.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would reform it ſelf from its Innovations, it muſt begin here, and bring down its Biſhop to his firſt Station; and diveſt him of that power to bring in or uphold any Innovations contrary to the primitive ſimplicity of the Goſpel. For while he ſtands in this exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, they can never reform themſelves farther than he pleaſes: And eſpecially while they look upon him as Infallible. For who can pretend to rectify any thing that proceeds from Infallibility.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Therefore another Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, The Popes Infallibility.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172742:8"/>This is a device which backs and ſupports his Exaltation, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the Thoughts and Spirits of men under him without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. For who dare mutter againſt an infallible Judge? But it might ſuffice one would think, to overturn the Infallibility of Popes, to ſee one Pope Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another; as <hi>Alexander Tertius</hi> and <hi>Victor Quartus</hi> did; who were both choſen Popes by the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals at the ſame time: and had both the ſame Authority given them. This was in the Year of our Lord, 1159. ſaith <hi>Buchol:</hi> And again in the Year 1439. Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> was depoſed by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Amadeus</hi> created Pope in his ſtead; and hence great Seditions aroſe. Now if you will have the Council here to be Infallible, then the Pope was Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible: Or if you will have the Pope to be infallible, then the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172742:8"/>Council was Fallible: So chuſe here whoſe Infallibility you will ſubvert, whether the Popes or the Councils. Take notice alſo of the acts of one Pope more, for I would not ennumerate many) Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VI. for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching of his Son <hi>Borgias,</hi> prepared a ſplendid Banquet, to which he invited certain principal great men; of which number Cardinal <hi>Adrian</hi> his familiar Friend was one. He ordered his Servants to ſet before them Wine that was poiſoned; and to ſet before him and his Son pure Wine. But Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſo ordered it, that the Wine that was poiſoned was ſet before himſelf and his Son; ſo they drank the poiſoned Wine, and the Gueſts drank pure Wine, Here was a great want of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick priviledge whom no deadly drink ſhould hurt: and ſo alſo of the Spirit of Infallibility,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172742:9"/>as to the preſervation of himſelf, and his Son. But that's not all I aim at. This wicked Murtherer had a little afore that poiſoned another, a Cardinal of <hi>Rome John Michael.</hi> Now ſhall we ſay, that ſo wicked a wretch was endowed with the Spirit of God, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the Spirit of Infallibility? Doth that teach ſuch Treachery and Wickedneſs? Surely every ſober man will abhor to think ſo.</p>
            <p>But I need not ſtand upon ſuch particular inſtances to ſhew the Fallibility of Popes: this will more generally appear as we go along diſcovering other Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For their Innovations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting and claſhing againſt the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Holy Apoſtles plainly manifeſt the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility and erring Spirit of the Popes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Innovation is the Selling of Pardons and Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172742:9"/>And this is another device helping to ſupport the Popes in their greatneſs, for it brings in much treaſure into the Popes Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers. And here I ſhall take notice of theſe three things. 1. That Pardons are Sold. 2. That they are a great ſupport to the Popes Exaltation. 3. That this Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abſolutely deſtroys the Popes Infallibility, and tranſplants him out of <hi>Peter</hi> into <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall prove that Pardons and Indulgences are Sold by the Popes: for ſome will deny any thing, though never ſo manifeſtly known; although the modeſter ſort of men under the Popes will not deny it. I ſhall paſs by their annual and more frequent ſelling of Pardons; and manifeſt their greater Fairs for the ſale of them. For they have invented certain great Fairs or Marts when men are to flock to <hi>Rome,</hi> to buy them.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172742:10"/>And theſe Fairs they call their Jubilees. They put the name <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee</hi> upon them, but they are plainly Faits for Pardons and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences. In the Jubilees Men went out free without Money: but here they are to pay their Money; therefore it is a Fair not a Jubilee. The firſt that invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe was <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII. in the year of our Lord 1300. And he ordained this great Fair (or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Jubilee) to be kept every hundred year. After him (but not next) <hi>Clemens</hi> VI. impatient of ſo long a ſtay for a Fair (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Life was not likely to reach to it) he reduced this their pecuniary Jubilee to every fiftieth year: So in the year 1350. he kept his great Fair. Then in the year 1400. <hi>Boniface</hi> IX. kept his great Fair. Another was kept in the year 1450. But now they began to think fifty years was too
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172742:10"/>long between Fair and Fair, ſo <hi>Xyſtus</hi> contracted them to twenty five years diſtance: and he kept his great Fair, Anno 1475. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologers have punctually expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the years; which puts the ſale of Pardons out of doubt, if any ſhould queſtion it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take notice that theſe are a great ſupport to the Popes Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſuch multitudes of men flocking from all parts to <hi>Rome,</hi> to buy their Pardons, that they could ſcarce walk one for another in that great City. In one of their Jubilees about two hundred men, its ſaid, were kill'd by the great Croud at the Bridge <hi>Sancti Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li,</hi> as they haſted for Pardons; ſome trod under foot, and ſome preſſed to death by the croud, and others thruſt into the River. And yet ſuch great Fairs or Marts would not ſatisfy the avarice of ſome of the <hi>Popes:</hi> but they ſent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172742:11"/>afterwards their pardons to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote places to be ſold. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> VI. the year after his Jubilee, ſent his Indulgences far off to be ſold. <hi>In Germaniam</hi> (ſaith my Author) <hi>atque alias longinquas Provincias Diplomata cum ampliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Jubilei Indulgentiis miſit, paſſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vendidit, propter eos qui Romam venire neglexerunt, vel venire non potuerunt.</hi> This was pretended to be for the ſakes of thoſe that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, or could not come to <hi>Rome</hi> at the Jubilee: By his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates he ſold them Pardons eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, <hi>paſſim vendidit Buchol. a Volater, anno</hi> 1500. This Simony hath greatly helped to enrich the <hi>Popes,</hi> and to bear them up in their high Exaltation in the World. Are theſe likely to be Succeſſors of the Apoſtles? and to ſit in the Apoſtolick Seat? Who ſaid, <hi>Love not the World, neither the things that are in the World.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172742:11"/>If any Man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him.</hi> 1 John 2.15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Innovation or inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Selling Pardons of Sins ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely deſtroys the Popes infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, tranſplanting him out of <hi>Peter</hi> into <hi>Simon Magus:</hi> that is, out of that Spirit that was in <hi>Peter,</hi> into that Spirit that was in <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> So that although the Pope pretend to be <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor: Yet he is fallen from <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> The Spirit that was in <hi>Peter</hi> abhorred the very thought of Selling the Spiritual gifts of God for Money. But the Spirit that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was of, and ſo the Popes are of, hath thought that the Spiritual gifts of God may be purchaſed with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. This is a great fall, to fall from one to whom the Key of the Kingdom of Heaven was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to one whom he Excluded
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172742:12"/>out of the Kingdom, and turned the Key againſt him: Saying. <hi>Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter: Thou art in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, and bond of Iniquity.</hi> And what was the ground of all this great Severity? only this; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſaith <hi>Peter) thou haſt thought, that the gift of God may be purchaſed with mony.</hi> Act. 8.18. to 24. And is not this very thought the Popes thought?</p>
            <p>Now I entreat you, weigh theſe things. Is not the pardon of Sins one of the greateſt gifts of God? And does not the Pope think that it may be purchaſed with Money, ſeeing he ſells it? Is not here the ſame thought that was in <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> for which he was ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely ſentenced by <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Excluded</hi> by him from all right in <hi>diſpenſing the Spiritual Gifts of God? Will</hi> you ſay that <hi>Peter</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned this thought in <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:172742:12"/>but is of another mind now, and approves of it in the Pope? If ſo, then you will condemn <hi>Peter</hi> as one faln from his own <hi>Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs,</hi> and not the <hi>Pope.</hi> If you ſay, the <hi>Pope</hi> doth not think as <hi>Simon</hi> did; he doth not think that the Spiritual Gift of God may be purchaſed with Money; then I ſay, He is ſtill the worſe, to ſell that Spiritual Gift, the Pardon of Sins for Money, which he thinks cannot be purchaſed for Money, For in ſo doing, he both robs them of their Money; and deceives their Souls, making them believe a Lie. And if the <hi>Caſe</hi> be ſo with the Pope, as it was with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who thought that the Gift of God might be purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Money, where is his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility?</hi> yea, where is his power to pardon Sin? Do you think that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> had power to pardon Sin? Or that one in his Sin hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172742:13"/>power ſo to do? Seeing he that was guilty of that Sinful, Carnal Thought, is excluded with him from having any part or lot in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing the Spiritual Gifts of God, except you will make <hi>Peter</hi> partial, in excluding one and not another, who is in the ſame fault. Again, doth not this alſo help to confirm that the Pope, being faln from <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> is that faln Star mentioned before?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another Innovation was that called <hi>Annatae.</hi> An Invention very near of Kin to the ſelling of Pardons: for this is a kind of ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Benefices.</hi> For they were not to enjoy <hi>Benefices,</hi> but under this Condition, that they ſhould pay half of the yearly profit into the Popes Treaſury. This, and the ſelling of Pardons hugely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed the Popes Treaſure. <hi>Quae res Blondo &amp; Platina teſtibus, Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices Romanos</hi> Bonifacii <hi>Succeſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172742:13"/>non minus Chriſtiani Orbis quam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbis Dominos reddidit.</hi> Theſe things made him Lord, as well of the whole Chriſtian World, as of the City. You may ſee more of this in the Year 1400 from the Nativity of Chriſt, quoted by <hi>Bucholcer.</hi> Where he ſaith, This Cuſtom all ſubmitted to, except in <hi>England,</hi> where the ſame was yielded to concerning the Biſhops, but not in other Benefices. Now if we may not call this Symony, what other name ſhall we give it? Seeing it is a kind of ſelling and buying of Spiritual Benefices, as they are called. And judge Ye whether <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or any other of the Apoſtles made filthy Lucre the Door, by which they let men into the Miniſtry, as the Popes do. And yet the Pope call'd this Treaſury, into which this is paid, <hi>The Apoſtolick Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> As if the Apoſtles had ſet up,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172742:14"/>or uſed ſuch an Earthly Treaſury. I mention this invention, becauſe it was one thing that greatly ſtrengthened the Popes in their high Exaltation: And alſo becauſe it impairs the Popes Infallibility, to ſee them act ſo contrary to the Spirit of the Holy Apoſtles of Chriſt; and yet giving it ſome Title to the Apoſtles, by calling this the Apoſtolick Treaſury.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Another Innovation, is the Popes Uſurpation of a Power over Emperors, Kings, Princes and People, in their Temporal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: So as, with a Word he can dethrone one, and have another ſet up, at his pleaſure, under his Dominion. Was there any thing that tended to this in any of the Apoſtles Practiſes, or Doctrine? Or for many Ages and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions after them? Were not the Biſhops in Subjection, as to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral affairs, under the Princes of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172742:14"/>the World? And not one of them authoritatively above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, until wicked <hi>Phocas</hi> gave the Precedency to ambitious <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> 3. And yet then, he did not give him power over himſelf, or over any ſecular Princes. So that this was an Uſurpation and Innovation of the Popes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: and was practiſed by ſome of them; and they got it decreed in ſome of their Councils. And <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. (who firſt inſtituted the Mercenary Jubilees, the ſame Year that he celebrated the firſt Jubilee,) Writ, <hi>That he was Lord in Temporals and Spirituals, in the whole World.</hi> Of whom it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by <hi>Platina</hi> thus: <hi>Qui Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poratoribus, Regibus, Principibus, Nationibus, populis terrorem potius quàm Religionem injicere conabatur: quique dare regna &amp; auferre, pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere homines ac reducere pro arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio animi conabatur,</hi> &amp;c. His en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172742:15"/>was to be a Terror to Emperors and Kings, Princes and People: To give Kingdoms, and take them away at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Now here take notice, that as the Popes Exaltation of himſelf was foreſhewed, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>So this Power and Dominion of the Popedom over Kings and Princes was foreſhewed, Rev.</hi> 17. <hi>ult.</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the repreſentation of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, there expounded to be a great City reigning over the Kings of the Earth. <hi>And the Woman which thou ſaweſt, is that great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which reigneth over the Kings of the Earth.</hi> Or nearer the Greek thus, <hi>Which hath a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom above the Kings of the Earth.</hi> Which Kingdom, if it be not the Popedom reigning over the Kings of the Earth, depoſing them at pleaſure, and Surrogating others in their ſtead, then I confeſs I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172742:15"/>know not what it is. But if other Circumſtances in that Chapter be conſidered with this, I think it will put this out of doubt: which here I cannot ſtand upon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out too great a diverſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption; but in its proper place, following where the Hierarchy of <hi>Rome</hi> comes to be ſpoken of, by Gods aſſiſtance, I ſhall demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>Another innovation is, <hi>The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing Dominion over mens Faith.</hi> It may be ſomething of this kind might begin before the Popes were ſo named: But however its upheld and practiſed by the Popes; and was not owned by the Apoſtles Doctrine; but is an Innovation contrary to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and purity of the Goſpel, whereſoever it is found. That it is a piece of Popery, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by them, is manifeſt by their puniſhing and cruel handling of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172742:16"/>thoſe that in Conſcience towards God, and faithfulneſs to his Truth, cannot ſubmit to thoſe their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Innovations, which they ſee to be ſo. But the Popes who have arrogated to themſelves Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and Dominion over the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Thrones of Kings and Princes, are not ſatisfied without the like dominion alſo over the Throne of God, the Conſcience; and except they model mens Faith, and caſt them all into one Mould: which thing the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles durſt not do. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> diſclaims this Dominion over mens Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. And he durſt not judge the Faith or Conſcience of the different be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Romans,</hi> when ſome of them kept a Day, and others kept it not; and when ſome of them did Eat Herbs, and others did Eat Fleſh; and both to the Lord as he judged: and therefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172742:16"/>them both, one againſt the other; and judged nothing but their judging of one another in ſo doing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4, 5, 6. And then he puts them in mind of Chriſt's Prerogative in this caſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. Saying, But why doſt thou judge thy Brother? Or why doſt thou ſet at nought thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt. But the Popes are not of <hi>Pauls</hi> mind; they will have men believe as they believe, or elſe Burn them alive. if this be not to exerciſe Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over mens Faith, and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, what is; And if this be not an innovation contrary to the ſimplicity, purity, mercy and meekneſs of the Goſpel, nothing is; which ſaith <hi>In meekneſs inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thoſe that oppoſe themſelves,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.25. not burning them, as is done under the Tyrannical Popedom.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:172742:17"/>
            <p n="7">7. But to back this their cruel Dominion over the Faith and Conſciences of men, and to palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate it, and make it take place, and go down with their people, they put the Name Heretick upon thoſe who cannot conform to their Innovations; that they may incenſe people againſt them. And this is another Innovation. And ſo they heap Innovation upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation. Whereas indeed and in truth, nothing is Hereſie but that which oppoſes the Truth of the Goſpel, delivered by Chriſt and his Holy Apoſtles. To op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe falſe Doctrine, and innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men is no Hereſie: But to bring in Innovations contrary to the Truth of the Goſpel, and to require ſubjection thereto, this is certainly Hereſie. Therefore let them that call, or count men Hereticks look to it, that they be not found the greateſt Hereticks,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172742:17"/>devouring innocent Lambs of Chriſt under that falſe notion. And indeed here is a notable Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem of Satan, whereby to make them that fear God, and abhor mens inventions, as Sheep fit for the Slaughter, even to fix oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>btious Terms upon them. For this begets an <hi>Odium</hi> in the minds of Blindfolded people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: and makes them through hatred ready for Butchers, and to execute Maſſacres and all manner of miſchief againſt the Faithful Servants of Chriſt, under that notion of being Hereticks. It muſt be under ſome ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, that the Great Whore makes her ſelf drunk with the Blood of Saints, and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus; ſuch as bear witneſs to him and his Truth againſt the Innovations of men.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And ſo that's another Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172742:18"/>namely, To rid men out of the Earth whom they call <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</hi> It's no ſin to deſtroy them, ſay they: Yea further, they have made it a Law, to Burn them. And this hath not been a dead Law: or like a Sword kept in a Scabbard; but hath been cruelly executed where the power of the Popedom hath prevailed. I am ſure this cruelty is an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: for there is no ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin from Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles; but poſitive Doctrin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Therefore that Law and ſuch other deſtructive Laws, and the execution of them, muſt needs be Innovations of men. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> our Lord ſaid, <hi>He came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them,</hi> Luke 9.54, 55, 56. But this Spirit that hath got into the Popedom comes to deſtroy mens lives, therefore is a Spirit contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Spirit of Chriſt. It's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Spirit crept in under the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172742:18"/>profeſſion of the Goſpel, not his. Chriſt Jeſus our Lord ſaid alſo concerning the <hi>Tares</hi> which his Servants would have been pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, <hi>Let them alone.</hi> How long were they to let them alone? Even <hi>till the end of the World.</hi> And then the Angels muſt do that work, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.29, 39. Men are not infallible, they may miſtake; Therefore the Lord ſaid to his own Servants, <hi>Let them alone,</hi> leſt ye pluck up Wheat with Tares: He will not have them do that rooting Work; but he will ſet thoſe to do that work that can more certainly diſtinguiſh between Tares and Wheat, even the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; &amp; they ſhall not do it neither, till his appointed time, even the end of the World. This therefore muſt needs be an Innovation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the command and will of Chriſt, to be doing this work, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any pretence, namely, to be rooting out Tares (if they really
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172742:19"/>be ſo) out of the Field of the World, before Chriſt's appointed time. Again, it's againſt that Golden Rule of Chriſt, <hi>As ye would that men ſhould do to you, ſo do ye to them,</hi> Mat. 7.12. Now would any man have others to burn him becauſe he cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as they believe? Would thoſe burning Popes have any of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches to burn them, or their People, becauſe they believe not as thoſe Reformed Churches believe? I think not. And yet it were but <hi>Lex talionis,</hi> like for like, if they did ſo. But I never heard of any call'd a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church, that ever did ſo: nor I hope ever will: altho they may have retained too much Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Cruelty ſtill unreformed of.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Another Innovation is, <hi>The Forbidding Marriage to their Gler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> (ſo called.) This is an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation alſo wherein they exerciſe Dominion over the Faith and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172742:19"/>Conſciences of others; and is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to the Scriptures. <hi>Have we not power,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>to lead about a Siſter, a Wife, as well as other Apoſtles, and as the Brethren of the Lord and Cephas,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.5. And again, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>A Biſhop muſt be blameleſs, the Husband of one Wife,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>The Deacons Wives muſt be grave,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Let the Deacons be the Husbands of one Wife.</hi> Hence you ſee its clear that they that are in the Miniſtry have power to Marry. But the Spirit of God dictating this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to <hi>Paul,</hi> immediately in the beginning of the next Chapter (which was a continuation of his diſcourſe about Marriage) he ſhews him an Innovation that ſhould ariſe contrary to this liberty, and he ſaith thus: <hi>Now the Spirit ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expreſly, that in the latter times ſome ſhall depart from the Faith, giving heed to ſeducing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172742:20"/>and Doctrines of Devils; ſpeaking lies in Hypocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron; forbidding to Marry, and commanding to abſtain from Meats,</hi> &amp;c. Here the Spirit of God ſeems to point at this very thing, even at the Popes prohibition of Marriage to Biſhops and Deacons, and ſuch as were to be admitted into the Miniſtry; becauſe it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows ſo quickly after that liberty of Biſhops and Deacons to be Marryed. And the words that accompany this prohibition of Marriage are worthy to be taken notice on. It ſhall be by perſons that are <hi>fallen,</hi> or departed from the pure Faith of the Goſpel (who ſhall have power over Biſhops, and are fallen) giving heed to ſeducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils; <hi>Speaking lies in Hypocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron</hi> (as hardned in their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences as a thing ſeared with an hot
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172742:20"/>Iron.) Then as a viſible Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of ſuch perſons he gives theſe two open Marks, that every one that runs may read them. <hi>They ſhall forbid Marriage,</hi> that's one: <hi>And command to abſtain from Meats,</hi> that's another: both which are found in the Popedom. They have power over Biſhops, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid their Marriage: and they are fallen very low from the purity of the Faith or Goſpel, as hath been ſhewed before: And theſe alſo impoſe it upon their People as a matter of Conſcience, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Meats. And the words <hi>Forbid</hi> and <hi>Command,</hi> ſhew that theſe things came in by force and power; not by a voluntary taking up. The Prohibition of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was very ſtiffly withſtood by the Clergy: but the power of the Pope prevailed againſt them. The Conteſt about this Innovation <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholcer</hi> expreſſes very plainly, in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172742:21"/>the words of <hi>Schaffnaburgenſis,</hi> ſhewing it to be an impoſition of <hi>Hiltebrand</hi> call'd <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1074. The Popes had need to keep the Scriptures from their People: for otherwiſe which of them could read this firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and not ſee the Error of the Popes in this matter, expreſſed ſo plainly, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.2, 4, 11, 12. and <hi>chap.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Their ſetting up Images and Pictures, and bowing to them, or before them in reverence to them, is another Innovation. And this is imputed to them for Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. For what is Idolatry, but bowing with reverence to an Idol? or worſhipping an Idol? And this is flatly contrary to the Second Commandment, the words where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are thus, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make unto thee any graven Image, or any likeneſs of any thing that is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172742:21"/>above, or in the Earth beneath, or in the Water under the Earth. Thou ſhalt not bow down thy ſelf to them, nor ſerve them: for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the iniquity of the Fathers upon the Children, unto the third and fourth Generation of them that hate me: and ſhewing mercy unto thouſands of them that love me, and keep my Commandments.</hi> What man reading this Commandment, and ſeeing or beholding their Images, and their bowing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, could think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but that they worſhipped them? Or who could think, but that this practiſe is a breach of this Commandment? Yea, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that have patronized this Idolatry, have been ſo ſenſible of their contradiction of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment hereby, that they durſt not let it ſtand: but have turned it out: becauſe it looks their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172742:22"/>Image-worſhip ſo full in the face: and is ſo plain that it would ſet the heart of every ſingle-hearted man againſt it. And this turning of the Second Commandment out of doors, is a plain demonſtration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them of their conſciouſneſs that they are guilty of the breach of it. For if they did not know that it were againſt their Idolatry, what need they turn it out of doors? And to deceive the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they have made up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ten, by dividing the laſt into two. Thus they dare tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with the Commands of God! Durſt any man whoſe Conſcience is not ſeared, expunge a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, which was writ with his own finger, and given with ſo great ſolemnity, as this was as well as the reſt, at Mount <hi>Sinai?</hi> I know the Sophiſtry of thoſe that would palliate this their Idolatry by frivolous diſtinctions
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172742:22"/>of Worſhip. But the Lord hath expreſt himſelf ſo fully againſt all appearance of Worſhip in this point, that he hath laid all their vain diſtinctions of Worſhip void. For whereas he hath in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment declared himſelf to be a jealous God; doth not this warn every man to flee from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appearance of the breach of it, leſt he by tampering with Images provoke the eyes of his Jealouſie? And doubtleſs this was ſpoken not only in reſpect of his own Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, who ſees the purpoſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of every heart; but alſo of the jealouſie of his faithful People, who would be offended thereby: and in offending them thereby, he is offended. Now let any judge; Is not here an appearance of Worſhip done to Images, when they bow before them, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them with reverence? If a jealous man ſhould ſee ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172742:23"/>and reverence between his. Wife and another Man, and ſee her ſo Idolize him, as they do their Images, would it not beget Jeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſie in him? Appearances of great reſpect beget Jealouſie. Now I ſay, why hath the Lord decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf to be a Jealous God in this Comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, but to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us thereby to ſhun all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Breach of it? according to the Exhortation of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Abſtain from all appearance of Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Breach of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, the Jews ſeverely ſmarted many times: and ſhall not ſuch as are called Chriſtians take warning thereby? Nothing provoked the Lord ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſhedding innocent Blood: and ſhall we think that ſuch things do not provoke his holy Spirit now? And a pretence of honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172742:23"/>God thereby will not excuſe men to him. The Jews when they had made a Calf in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and Sacrificed to it, and Feaſted with thoſe Sacrifices, this was done in pretence to the Lord, who had brought them out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi> Therefore when <hi>Aaron</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a Day to do Sacrifice to the Calf, he proclaimed it thus, <hi>To morrow is a Feaſt to the Lord,</hi> Exod. 32.5. You ſee this was pretended to be done to the Lord, &amp; the people came upon that Proclamation, as keeping a Feaſt to the Lord, and did Eat and Drink, and make merry; and in their Sacrifice c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated their deliverance out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> But they would have that Calf to repreſent their Deliverer, and therefore attributed that Title to the thing repeſenting; which was due only to the Lord, whom they would repreſent. For we cannot imagine that they, who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:172742:24"/>ſo lately had ſeen the wonders of the Lord, in bringing them out with a high hand, and went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in a Pillar of a Cloud and Fire, could believe that Calf to be their Deliverer; both becauſe it was made after they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; and alſo becauſe it was made of their own Ear-Rings, and Gold which they gave to <hi>Aaron</hi> to make it of: but they put <hi>Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num pro re ſignificata;</hi> the ſign for the thing ſignified; which the Lord will not approve of in ſuch caſe. And therefore in this place and to this Innovation I may here add their Idolatry uſed in their Sacrifice of the Maſs, worſhipping the Sign for the thing ſignified. Namely, their worſhipping of that which their own hands have made; which was always counted Idolatry in Scripture. Their Land (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) <hi>is full of Idols: they worſhip the Work of their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172742:24"/>own hands, that which their own Fingers have made. And the mean Man boweth down, and the Great Man humbleth himſelf; therefore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them not,</hi> Iſa. 2.8, 9. And again in the New Teſtament its ſaid, <hi>The reſt of men which were not killed with theſe Plagues, yet repented not of the Works of their Hands, that they ſhould not worſhip Devils and Idols of Gold, and Silver, and Braſs, and Stone, and Wood, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can ſee, nor hear, nor walk,</hi> Rev. 9.20. Now conſider, is not this the Work of their own hands, that which their own Fingers have made? Is it not a God of their own making? Do they not firſt make the Bread or Waſers, and then make it a God by ſpeaking a few words? And is it not ſuch a God as can neither ſee, nor hear, nor walk, nor ſpeak? By which Characters Idols are frequently deſcribed: and will you have Chriſt Jeſus to come
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172742:25"/>under the deſcription of Idols, and make him like them? <hi>The Idols of the Heathen have Mouths, but they ſpeak not, Eyes but they ſee not, Ears but they hear not.</hi> They are known to be Idols, becauſe they can neither ſpeak, nor ſee, nor hear: and will you make him like one of them? Read and conſider, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.15, 16. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>Where you may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, not to hear, not to ſpeak, not to ſee, not to ſmell, not to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, not to walk are made notes of an Idol to know them by.</hi> And will you now make our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom the World was made, like a Dumb Idol? Will you make that to be he, which was only left for a Memorial of him? <hi>Do this as often as ye do it in remembrance of me,</hi> ſaith he. He makes it but a Sign, for a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of him.</p>
            <p>I do believe that many may be verily perſwaded, that the Bread
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:172742:25"/>and Wine are really the Body and Blood of Chriſt: and ſo uſe it with great reverence, as if it were he; and that they think they do honour him thereby. But it is great diſhonour done to him, if you well conſider the thing. For firſt it brings him under the Circumſtances of the Idols of the Heathen, as hath been ſhewed. 2. To offer him up again, invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates that one Sacrifice of himſelf upon the Croſs, once for all, by which he hath for ever perfected them that are ſanctified.</p>
            <p>But I know you ſtand upon the literal words of Chriſt, <hi>This is my Body.</hi> And therein I can bear with you a little, becauſe many may think, that they verily obey Chriſt therein. But if you well weigh it, you will find that thoſe words are not to be taken literally, but figuratively, as many other of his expreſſions were: as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172742:26"/>
               <hi>I am the Door, I am the true Vine, my Father is the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman:</hi> Take one more, which comes near to that ſaying, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> namely this, <hi>Except ye Eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and Drink his Blood, ye have no life in you,</hi> John 6.53. Some took that in a literal ſenſe, as you do thoſe words, <hi>This is my Body.</hi> But let us mind his own expoſition of them; for that comes near to the Caſe in hand. <hi>The words that I ſpeak unto you; they are Spirit, and they are Life.</hi> (What do you talk of the Fleſh) <hi>The Fleſh profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing: Its the Spirit that quickeneth,</hi> John 6.63. Whereby he ſhews plainly, that this Eating of his Fleſh he ſpake of, was the receiving and nouriſhing of his Spirit in our Hearts, which gives us life; a Spiritual Life in him. A like expreſſion to this he uſed to the Woman of <hi>Samaria, John</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:172742:26"/>4.14. where he compares the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving and embracing of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to drinking of Water: the words are theſe, <hi>But whoſoever drinketh of the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never Thirſt: but the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a Well of Water, ſpringing up into everlaſting. Life.</hi> You ſee by Water, he underſtood Spirit, and by Fleſh and Blood he underſtood Spirit: which were Metaphorical expreſſions. And ſo here in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> he ſpake after the ſame manner: For when as he ſaith, <hi>The Fleſh profiteth nothing,</hi> to what end ſhould we imagine, that he left his Fleſh to be eaten.</p>
            <p>But then as for the Offering of him up by a Prieſt. This is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion into the Mediatorſhip of Chriſt, who only could offer up himſelf to God: He being both the Sacrifice, and the Prieſt ſet
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172742:27"/>apart by God for that work, whom all the Prieſts under the Law ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifyed. And he did this himſelf, <hi>Once for all. And there remains no more Sacrifice for Sin. For by one Offering he hath perfected for ever them that are Sanctified.</hi> You may read that word <hi>Once</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many times in the 9th. and 10th. Chapters of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> whereby is ſhewed the Difference between the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Law, which were types, and that one Sacrifice of Chriſt, which was the ſubſtance: How they were offered often, becauſe they could not make the Comers thereunto perfect as pertaining to the Conſcience: but this Sacrifice of Chriſt was offered but <hi>Once,</hi> becauſe it is of Efficacy at once offering, to make the comers to it perfect, as pertaining to the Conſcience, that is, to clear their conſcience, that they may draw
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:172742:27"/>near to God, in full aſſurance of Faith, having their Hearts ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from an evil Conſcience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. Many things might fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſpoken upon this point; but it being much controverted by others, I haſten to other things. Only give me leave to commend one thing worthy to be read by all that are in doubt upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. And that is the Epiſtle of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſent to the Captives in <hi>Babylon.</hi> You may find it in the <hi>Apocripha;</hi> its the laſt Chapter of <hi>Baruch,</hi> the whole Chapter. Where, ſetting aſide the Matter that their Idols were made of, their deſcription by their impotency to do any thing, or help themſelves, beſide many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances, may as well be applyed to that which is called the Hoſt, as it was to them; whereby they are known to be no Gods. They cannot ſpeak,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:172742:28"/>they cannot feel if they be gnawed upon by Worms, they cannot ſave themſelves from Thieves or Robbers, but ſtand in need to be kept with Locks and Bars from Robbers, if you ſet many Candles before them, they cannot ſee one, there is no Breath in them, they are born by men, having no feet to go with, whereby they declare unto men, that they are nothing worth, if they fall to the Ground at any time, they cannot riſe up again of themſelves: nor can they move themſelves. By theſe things ye may know that they are no Gods. Many things of like ſort you may read of them in that Chapter, whereby, ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> you may know that they are no Gods; therefore fear them not. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Now I pray you conſider what diſhonour you do to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to exhibit him to the world in ſuch a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:172742:28"/>Dreſs; ſo fully agreeing with the deſcription of the Heathen Idols. May not the Heathen ſay, What is your God better than our God? Miſerable are they, ſaith <hi>Solomon, And in dead things is there hope, who called them Gods which are the Works of mens Hands.</hi> Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon, Chap.</hi> 13.10.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Another diſmal Innovation is depriving people of the free uſe of the Holy Scriptures in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, this ſhews the Popedom to be a Dominion, point blank oppoſite to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. For his Kingdom is a Kingdom of light: but the Popedom is a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of darkneſs. Chriſt was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for a light to us: but the Pope brings darkneſs. <hi>I will give thee for a Light to the Gentiles, that thou maiſt be my Salvation unto the end of the Earth,</hi> Iſa. 49.6. The Light
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:172742:29"/>is in order to Salvation not dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And the ſame Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> perſonates Chriſt ſpeaking thus, <hi>Chap.</hi> 51.4. <hi>Hearken unto me my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and give Ear unto me O my Nation: for a Law ſhall proceed from me, and I will make my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to reſt for a Light of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> But the Popedome will not let his Law and his Judgment to reſt for a Light of the People, but hides it from them; and as Thieves and Robbers they rob them of that which is for Salvation unto the end of the Earth. Therefore the true Apoſtles were ſent forth to turn men from darkneſs to the Light; and by that means, from the Power of Satan (which is in the Darkneſs) unto God; that ſo they might receive forgiveneſs of Sins, and an inheritance (in that Light) <hi>among them that are San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by Faith in Chriſt,</hi> Acts 26.18. And therefore the happy State
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:172742:29"/>of Believers is called <hi>an inheritance in the Light,</hi> Col. 1.12. Eph. 5.8.</p>
            <p>But Popery gives an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Darkneſs. It matters not how dark people be kept, if they have but Mony enough, they may obtain an inheritance in the Darkneſs therewith, ſuch as it is. Is it not manifeſt to all, that here is a Kingdom of darkneſs ſet up under the Popedom, working quite contrary to the Kingdom of Chriſt, which ſtands in the Light?</p>
            <p>And as by this Innovation, they moſt clearly ſhew their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be contrary to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt: So alſo hereby they manifeſt themſelves to be <hi>Evil Workers,</hi> departed from the Truth of the Goſpel. For why do they deprive people of the free uſe of the Scripture, but becauſe it diſcovers their evil Deeds; their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:172742:30"/>deeds of darkneſs? And therefore leſt people ſhould ſee their works of darkneſs which it diſcovers, they put out that Candle: or hide the light of it from them, by clothing the Scriptures with the Hairy Sack-cloth of their own Comments, for the ſaving of their innovations from the ſharp Edge thereof. Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, <hi>the Truth and the Life,</hi> hath told us plainly, <hi>That he that doth Truth cometh to the Light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God. But</hi> (on the other hand) <hi>every one that doth evil hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Light, neither cometh to the Light, leſt his deeds ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved,</hi> John 3.20, 21. Its a plain demonſtration of an evil doer, to hate the Light.</p>
            <p>I know ſome are ſo ſeared, that they have confidence (I may ſay impudence) to defend this reſtraint of the Scriptures from the people:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:172742:30"/>becauſe ſay they, The liberty of having and reading the Scriptures is a means to beget and foment Errors and Hereſies in the Church. To this I anſwer, Firſt, This judgment is directly contrary to the Judgment of Chriſt: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its a falſe and forged Opinion. For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Ye err not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures:</hi> but Popery ſaith, Ye will Err if ye know the Scriptures, therefore ye ſhall be debar'd of them. Thus directly oppoſite to Chriſt, is that work, and he that defends it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29. Secondly, I give this anſwer, <hi>The cauſe of this falſe aſſertion or ſhift,</hi> in ſaying, That the Scritures are a means or cauſe of Errors among the people, is this. They that are trained up under the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh innovations, take thoſe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations for Truth, and the Truth it ſelf for Error. So they call that Error and Hereſie, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:172742:31"/>to thoſe innovations. And herein they fall under the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Woe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Woe to them that call evil good, and good evil: that put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to go on with this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novated Darkneſs. They hereby not only ſhew their oppoſition to Chriſt and his Kingdom; and make themſelves known to be evil Doers: but alſo herein they ſhew themſelves moſt cruel Tyrants againſt their own people, keeping them, as it were in a Dungeon and Chains of Darkneſs, where they muſt not make uſe of their own Eyes, nor have the Benefit of the comfortable light of the Sun: but they muſt ſee only with others Eyes; and by the light of thoſe dim Candle-lights, which burn blew through the Damp of their Pit, which they hand to them in dark Lanthrons. To
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:172742:31"/>ſpeak plainly, they muſt have little or no light, but ſuch as is obfuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and dimmed with their poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous innovations; and that muſt be held forth to them by perſons ſufficiently leavened with their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt inventions. They muſt not make uſe of their own Eyes, to ſee with their own Eyes and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, the comfortable Sunſhine of thoſe pure Truths which ſhine forth in the plain and uncorrupted words of the Goſpel, left upon record. This is Tyranny upon the Souls of people; to which the Bondage of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of Old <hi>Babylon</hi> was but a ſmall matter; ſeeing that chiefly was upon the Body, but this is upon the Soul. So that their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled people cannot ſay, Their Soul is their own. But they are the Slaves and Souls of men, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling that very expreſſion of them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.3. For how can a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:172742:32"/>Man ſay, that his Soul is his own, when he cannot make uſe of the Faculties of it? But muſt be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in things Spiritual reſtrained to the Senſe and Will of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>This is an Innovation of great conſequence: for it is as a Lock and Key upon all their other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, to keep them ſafe from being aſſaulted. So that hereby they Eſtabliſh themſelves in their Kingdom of Darkneſs? even as Satan holds his Kingdom in men, as long as he can keep them in darkneſs: but where light comes, Satan falls like Lightning: and even ſo where the free uſe of the Scriptures comes in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, their Innovations muſt needs fall. But what wickedneſs is this, that for the upholding an earthly Kingdom, they care not what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of Millions of Souls, but let them periſh in the darkneſs by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:172742:32"/>their will. For Children of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they muſt be kept; and not be ſuffered to become Children of the Light, if they can help it. The Holy Apoſtles of Chriſt gave this Teſtimony of the Scriptures, <hi>That they are able to make one wiſe unto Salvation, through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus; and that they are given forth by inſpiration of God; and are profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Righteouſneſs, that the man of God may be perfect, thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furniſhed unto all good Works,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15, 16, 17. What's the reaſon then that men ſhould be envied, the comfortable uſe and benefit of them? Is there any true reaſon can be given for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of them, but this? <hi>That men would by them be inſtructed and furniſhed againſt the Innovations of the Popedom;</hi> and ſo run into that which they call Hereſie? But
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:172742:33"/>what deſperate wickedneſs, and ſcared Conſciences hath God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven people up unto, that dare thus in oppoſition to the inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Spirit of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Souls of People, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of ſo great helps, and furtherance of their Salvation! This is a Robbery far greater than any earthly Robbery. And yet they muſt be called Holy Fathers, who have been the greateſt Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the World.</p>
            <p>May we not here greatly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that the Myſtery of Iniquity doth here lurk, where ſuch care is taken to keep out the light of the Scriptures from men, leſt thereby they ſhould diſcover it? Yea, may we not rather detect that Myſtery of Iniquity to be here, where ſo many Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons contrary to the Holy Scriptures are found? and ſuch innovations as turn the profeſſion of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:172742:33"/>into a Stream quite contrary to its own nature? To work wickedly and contrary to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and yet pretend there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in holineſs and ſerving of God: What's this but Iniquity under a Myſtery; wickedneſs vailed with pious pretences? And what is the Myſtery of Iniquity, but Iniquity in a Myſtery? Iniquity under pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pretences, which makes it a Myſtery? But thoſe pretences can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alter the nature of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but only put a fair Gloſs upon it: for wickedneſs is wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs whereſoever it is found; and the fair pretences put upon it cannot change its nature, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dazle the Eyes, and Minds of men, and make it myſterious to them. The ſhedding of ſo much innocent Blood, as hath been ſhed in Maſſacres, and Fires, and by other ways, doth not change the nature of that wickedneſs, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:172742:34"/>the name of Hereticks upon thoſe who were ſo deſtroyed: only that ignominious Title may cover it to the ignorant, and make that cruelty ſeem to them, a pious thing; and ſo make that Iniquity a Myſtery. And in like manner Idolatry or bowing to Images may be made a Myſtery, by pretending it to be a reverenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and thanking him for ſuch or ſuch a Saint, or ſuch like conſiderations: when as the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf is directly oppoſite to his command, and bears no other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but of an idolatrous worſhip, contrary to the ſecond Commandment; which they dare not let ſtand in the common ſight of their people, for fear of its diſcovering their Idolatry. Now (not to name the reſt of theſe their innovations here) what greater wickedneſs is there, then theſe three, namely, ſhedding innocent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:172742:34"/>Blood; worſhipping Images, or Gods of their own making; and robbing people of ſo great a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to their Souls, as the Holy Scriptures in their purity might be? And all the pretences they can put upon theſe Evils, can but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe them, and make them a Myſtery, but they cannot change the nature of them.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Another Innovation is that invention of putting their people upon the pattering over ſo many <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> that they need a String of Beads to number them by. And here we may ſtand ſtill and wonder that men that pretend themſelves ſo profound Doctors and Fathers in the Church of Chriſt, ſhould ſhew themſelves to be ſo blind or wicked. So blind, as to think that God is well pleaſed with Lip-labour; or ſo wicked as to make people believe that he is ſo. Surely
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:172742:35"/>they know that Chriſt Jeſus our great Doctor or Teacher hath ſaid, <hi>When ye pray uſe not vain Repetitions, as the Heathen do: for they think that they ſhall be heard for their much ſpeaking. Be not ye therefore like unto them,</hi> Mat. 6.7, 8. But theſe Doctors make their people like the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then herein. The Lord requires ſuch worſhip as is done in <hi>Spirit and in Truth,</hi> John 4.23.24. Its not vain Lip-labour that's accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to him: but my Son, <hi>give me thy Heart,</hi> ſaith he. <hi>He hates drawing near him with the Lips, and the Heart far from him.</hi> Its pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Spirit, and with the underſtanding alſo that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. If theſe great Doctors know not theſe things, they are not fit to be Teachers or Guides in the Church of Chriſt: and if they do know them, the greater is their wickedneſs to teach people
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:172742:35"/>to do things that are ſo contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, and thereby to make them like the Heathen, thinking to be heard for much babling.</p>
            <p>But to what end ſhould they repeat ſo many <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> with their <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> every day? Is <hi>Mary</hi> at hand every Hour to be ſaluted by them? Is ſhe preſent continually all over the large Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Popedom, to be ſaluted by them all, that patter that Salutation ſo often over? Or do they hereby worſhip her as a God, thinking her to be Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent? Its hard to know for what good end this Cuſtom was invented. For my part I can ſee no other end in it but this; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to keep People buſie; and ſo to divert them from more ſerious thoughts, leſt their Conſciences ſhould be ſet at work to ponder the Path of Life; and whether
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:172742:36"/>they were in it or no: and ſo ſhould enter into more ſerious and deep conſideration of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual condition. Or is it becauſe they have led them out of the Road of peace by their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous innovations, and muſt give them ſome thing to do to pacify the requirings of their Conſcience? For there is even in the Heathens a Conſcience that muſt be ſatisfied, or diverted by ſome manner of worſhip or other: and therefore they ſatisfy their conſcience as well as they can, by worſhipping ſomething, what they think to be a God. And is this the Caſe here? How like then do they make their people to the Heathen. But I conſider there may be another end in it to keep people thus buſie, and that is, leſt they ſhould grow too wiſe for their Teachers, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving their ſpare time, in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Truth; and acquainting
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:172742:36"/>themſelves with the Ground of thoſe things they practice, and walk in: and ſo ſhould come to ſee the rotten Foundation, upon which all their ſuperſtitious and idle inventions are grounded. Filling their Hands full is a way to divert them from ſuch ſcrutiny or ſearch; that ſo they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may ſit at reſt and eaſe in their dominion of innovations o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the People. For find them work enough, and that will keep them buſie, and divert them from prying into the Myſteries of their Innovations, and ſo keep them off from turning againſt them for impoſing ſuch groundleſs imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations upon them. For the Minds of Man muſt have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to buſie it ſelf withal, being of a reſtleſs inquiring prying tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Another Innovation is that of <hi>Cardinals:</hi> of which there is
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:172742:37"/>no mention at all in Scripture: not one word of ſuch a Conclave or Combination. Theſe are as it were the very Hinges upon which the <hi>Popedom</hi> doth hang, and turn it ſelf; and therefore are they rightly called <hi>Cardinals,</hi> as much as to ſay <hi>Hinges</hi> from <hi>Cardo</hi> a Door-hinge. Theſe being Popes Creatures bear up the Pope after they have ſet him up. And one with another as one Head, they cheriſh and enforce the Popiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, wherein his Kingdom ſtands: and they therein as the chief Princes of that Kingdom. Theſe having no Foundation in Scripture muſt needs be an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: And when the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scourge comes to ſweep away all refuges of Lyes; theſe, being one chief falſe refuge of the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and main Pillars thereof, muſt tumble with it. The Pope, he is the Door through which the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:172742:37"/>Popedom of Innovations hath come in: And the Cardinals, they are the Hinges upon which he turns, bearing up him, and his Kingdom of Innovations: and together they will fall, when the Myſtery of Iniquity ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved. Theſe are of the number of thoſe Merchants of the Earth, which ſhall lament the fall of the <hi>Babylon</hi> of Innovations, when mens Eyes ſhall be opened, and no man ſhall buy their Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize any more, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be but the vain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of men which profit them not. For ſo hath our Lord Jeſus Chriſt taught us, ſaying, <hi>In vain do ye worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines the Precepts of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, which are introduced and upheld by Popes, beſides many others, which it would be too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious here to recite. It may be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:172742:38"/>the Lord may ſtir up the Spirits of ſome others to purſue them further. But theſe here mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are ſufficient to let any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what it is I call Popery, namely, theſe and ſuch other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations upheld under the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. For I would not have any to think (as I have ſignified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) that I do by Popery under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand whatſoever is found among the Papiſts: for I do not by Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comprehend thoſe ancient and good Truths, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was at firſt eſtabliſhed in; and many of which they may yet retain: as namely, all thoſe wholeſome and ſound Doctrines that are agreeable to the uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Scriptures; and which nouriſh a pious and good Life; and which teach to walk humbly with God, and faithfulneſs to his precepts; and equity and juſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among men, to do to others as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:172742:38"/>we would have them to do to us; and which teach charity and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and good works; and which lead to an inward walking with God: and to an innocent life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men; and ſuch like. I call nothing of this kind, popery: but only, as I ſay, Innovations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the precious Truths of the Goſpel. I own that there are precious Truths among them, but much entangled and clouded with abundance of innovations mixed therewith. Therefore it was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for me, for Peoples better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, thus to diſtinguiſh, between the one and other: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the good and primitive Truths; and the inventions of men crept in afterwards.</p>
            <p>That in the inventions of men or Innovations, we may find the Apoſtacy of the Romiſh Church: which comprehends theſe things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:172742:39"/>
            <p>In their Innovations we ſhall find,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Myſtery of Iniquity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> Spiritual.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Babylon</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The great Whore, that ſitteth upon many Waters, which is the Mother of Harlots. Which things call for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſay, in their Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we ſhall find the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of Iniquity. And that may eaſily be found out by the plain and full deſcription of him that is head in it, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3, 4. Firſt, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that there muſt be a falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the purity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; which implys that the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of inquity was to ariſe where the purity and truth of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel had been profeſſed, and lived in, but was fallen from, and in the ſame place the Myſtery of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity ſhould ariſe, in which My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:172742:39"/>there ſhould be one thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. (1.) He ſhould be a <hi>Son of Perdition:</hi> or a Son of <hi>Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> a deſtroyer, and ſo to be deſtroyed. And ſo the Angel of the bottomleſs Pit, which is a faln Star, hath the ſame name, both in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. being called <hi>Abaddon,</hi> and <hi>Apollyon,</hi> which ſignify a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer. For they belong both to one and the ſame deſtroying My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, as head therein, and ſo have the ſame name. (2.) He ſhould be one that <hi>oppoſeth, and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is Worſhipped.</hi> (3.) <hi>He ſits in the Temple of GOD,</hi> (the Church) <hi>Shewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> Now who is there that Anſwers this Deſcription ſo much as he that is head in the Popedom? Whether it be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man, or a conjoyned po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, or combination of more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:172742:40"/>Firſt, he or they that ſit in that power, are fallen from the purity, ſimplicity, and innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Goſpel of Chriſt into the deſtructive inventions and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of men: by reaſon of which Millions of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men profeſſing Chriſt, have been deſtroyed by Maſſacres and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways: therefore Secondly, the Title of <hi>the Son of Perdition: a Deſtroyer, Abaddon, and Apollyon,</hi> doth aptly fit that Power or them in it. Thirdly, he is an <hi>Oppoſer,</hi> exalting himſelf above all that's called God. What is called God in Scripture? Firſt, God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty himſelf, He oppoſes him, and exalts himſelf above him, in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling and controuling his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, leaving out what he pleaſes, or finds to be againſt his earthly Kingdom: one thing is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandment, which is ſo ſtrongly enforced with argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:172742:40"/>even by God himſelf, to be inviolabſy obſerved, without any ſhew of the breach thereof, for fear of exaſperating his jealouſie, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring of puniſhment upon their poſterity, that he that controuls it, muſt needs be an oppoſer of God. Secondly, He oppoſes Chriſt, and his Kingdom; bringing in an earthly Kingdom of darkneſs, in oppoſition to Chriſt's Spiritual Kingdom of Light. Thirdly, He oppoſes and exalts himſelf above all Magiſtrates (called Gods in Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1, 6. <hi>John</hi> 10.34, 35.) putting down and ſetting up as he pleaſes. He hath a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom above them all. The Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is a Kingdom above Kings of the Earth. Therefore he and they that bear the Power in that Kingdom, are this exalted one. Fourthly, He hath his Seat in the Temple of God the Church. The Church is called the Temple of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:172742:41"/>God in the New Teſtament, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? For Ye are the Temple of the living God.</hi> Here this man of Sin, <hi>this Son of Perdition hath his Seat, He ſitteth in the Temple of God,</hi> which clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinguiſhes him from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Potentates, which have their Seed in the Civil Government. Read 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. Where, under this exalted one you will find, <hi>The Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> ſubjoyned and entailed, as patronized by him. So finding out that exalted Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer, finds out the Myſtery of iniquity; <hi>which conſiſts in Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Inventions of men,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of Chriſt Jeſus, and his Holy Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>I know ſome good people take this Myſtery of Iniquity to be that natural ſinful State, wherein ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all men live.</p>
            <p>But for the better information
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:172742:41"/>of their underſtandings, I deſire thoſe that think ſo, to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That this Myſtery of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty here ſpoken of, <hi>is a Circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Myſtery,</hi> which had its riſe ſince the publication of the Goſpel; and ſhall have its period again in due time before inqiuity have an end. It began indeed to work in ſome mens Spirits in the Apoſtles days; but was letted that it could not break forth, and come to its heigth. <hi>It doth already work,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Only he who now let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth will let until he be taken out of the way,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.7. An Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my letted it until he was taken out of the way. The perſecuting Emperors while they ſtood, they kept down the profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity very much, by frequent perſecutions, ſo that there was more power of Chriſtianity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, while Perſecution laſted. But when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:172742:42"/>got the Dominion, and gave full Scope to the profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and drew in Nations into an outward conformity thereto, by his noble and courteous uſage of thoſe he conquered; then that which letted was taken out of the way: and then by degrees ſprang up the magnifying of the outward form, and imagined pious addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were made thereto, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which by little and little the Myſtery crept up, till it came to its height, For it roſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pious pretences; and that was it that blinded people ſo, that they could not perceive it. But as the Myſtery of Iniquity had a Beginning and growth in this wiſe, ſince the Apoſtles times, ſo it ſhall have a period. The Lord will bring no nought this Myſtery again, and conſume it with the Spirit of his mouth, and deſtroy it with the brightneſs of his coming. It
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:172742:42"/>ſhall fall with the deſolation of the great Whore, upon whoſe Fore-head it is writ, being upheld by her: and ſhe ſhall fall before Iniquity have an end, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear afterwards. And therefore I ſay, this Myſtery of Iniquity, is not the common ſinful ſtate of wickedneſs, that men have lived in, in all Ages of the World, which have born the open Face of wickedneſs; but it is a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and vailed Myſtery; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a beginning and an ending in this latter age of the World, ſince Chriſt. It is a Myſtery of wickedneſs wrapped up in an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Mantle of pretended Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. And when the Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens the Eyes of Princes, that have given their power to it, to ſee it; they ſhall hate the Whore, <hi>and Eat her Fleſh, and burn her with Fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16. And this they ſhall do before the common State
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:172742:43"/>of wickedneſs have an end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> as the Myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is couched under the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of men: So in them we ſhall find that which is called <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> Spiritually. <hi>Sodom</hi> literal was a place of great Violence and Uncleanneſs: How violently did they beſet <hi>Lots</hi> Houſe, only for the fulfilling of their Brutal uncleanneſs? And hath not as great violence been uſed upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Innovations, for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of their ſpiritual unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in going a Whoring after the inventions or innovations of men? Are not the Streets or ways of theſe innovations as full of danger and violence, where all are root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out that ſtand againſt them; or at leaſt violently handled? What hath been the Ground of all that violence of late done in <hi>France,</hi> but innovations of men, to turn them to embrace mens inventions?
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:172742:43"/>That great word (if I may not ſay Boaſt) of converting about two Millions of people into the Boſom of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (for which might be expected a grateful acknowledgment from the Pope) what is it more then a converting of them to their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations by their violence? For they were Chriſtians before: they did not convert them to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, but only to the Popiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations. I name this becauſe it is ſo freſh in every ones mind: But violence hath all along atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Innovations of the Popes. And beſide the ſpiritual unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of going a Whoring after mens inventions; How great a Provocation to brutal uncleanneſs is made, by that one Innovation of prohibiting Marriage to their Clergy; and otherwiſe by Licenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stewes, and making people believe they have pardon for their
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:172742:44"/>Sins, for a little mony, eſpecially if they be Venial, as they count ſome. None I think are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo Mortal, as oppoſing their Innovations. That's made He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie with them, and worthy of death, and damnable.</p>
            <p>Again, in theſe Innovations, <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpiritually ſo called is found. <hi>Egypt</hi> was a Houſe of Bondage to the natural <hi>Iſraelite:</hi> So theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations are a Houſe of Bondage to the Spiritual <hi>Iſraelite.</hi> The true Seed that deſires to follow Chriſt fully, finds Bondage in all Innovations or Inventions of men. And they that impoſe humane Traditions and Inventions upon peoples Conſciences, are like the Task-maſters of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpiritual Seed. For the true Seed, the Chaſte Virgin, hates ſubjection of Spirit to any other in things Spiritual, ſave to her own Lord Chriſt Jeſus. His Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:172742:44"/>and Council ſhe delights to lye under. But the hard task of the impoſition of mans wiſdom upon her Spirit is grievous Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to her, and cauſes her Spirit to groan for deliverance. And in time the Lord will work deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance for the ſpiritual <hi>Iſraelite;</hi> as he did for the literal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, In Innovations we find Babylon the Great.</hi> Many words uſed in former times both before and under the Law, are transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or brought over, and put upon things under the Goſpel, or New Covenant: either becauſe they are under the like Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or were prefigured by things aforegoing. As to give one Example or two; the Tabernacle and Temple which were made by men, and made of Wood, and Stone, and Gold, and Silver, and Braſs, and Iron, Theſe were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the preſence of God to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:172742:45"/>in, and to dwell in. But in the fulneſs of time thoſe were laid aſide again, and yet the names of them retained and put upon other things, where the preſence of God was to reſide. As namely, Chriſts Body, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and in three daies I will raiſe it up again.</hi> This ſpake he of his Body, putting the name <hi>Temple</hi> upon it. Again the ſame word <hi>Temple</hi> is put upon his Church, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo upon the Bodies of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. <hi>What, know ye not that your Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt which is in you.</hi> And again ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If any man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy: for the Temple of God is holy, which Temple ye are,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.17. So <hi>Tabernacle</hi> is uſed in like manner, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I muſt put off this my Tabernacle.</hi> I might inſtance in many things,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:172742:45"/>but I would not digreſs too much from my preſent ſcope and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is to ſhew that the name <hi>Babylon</hi> is alſo put upon ſomething under the Goſpel, which <hi>Babylon</hi> of old reſembled, or did prefigure. And that is, that Dominion that ſtands in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations or Inventions of men. This is called, <hi>Babylon the Great,</hi> Rev. 17.5.</p>
            <p>Now why the name <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould be put upon that Power and Dominion that ſtands in Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under the Goſpel times, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the like circumſtances of both <hi>Old Babylon</hi> and <hi>New,</hi> and the like expreſſions given forth of both, and I think you may eaſily be perſwaded thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Old Babylon</hi> was called, <hi>The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Kingdoms,</hi> Iſa. 13.19. and the <hi>Lady of Kingdoms,</hi> Iſa. 47.5, 7. And <hi>Babylon the Great</hi> is counted no leſs, ſeeing ſhe reigneth over
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:172742:46"/>Kings of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.18.</p>
            <p>There was the ſame exalted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of heart in both: for <hi>Old Babylon,</hi> ſaid in her heart, <hi>I am, and none elſe beſides me, I ſhall not ſit as a Widdow, neither ſhall I ſee the loſs of Children,</hi> Iſa. 47.8. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon the Great,</hi> ſaith in her heart, <hi>I ſit a Queen and am no Widdow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow,</hi> Rev. 18.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Old Babylon</hi> was a place of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity to the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> and <hi>New Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Babylon the Great,</hi> hath been a place of far greater Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity to the true ſpiritual <hi>Iſraelite.</hi> That was but for a few years, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Seventy. But this hath laſted long, even many Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, namely ever ſince Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions got head. That was a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity far leſs cruel than this latter Captivity hath been. They both of them have exerciſed force upon the Conſciences of People.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:172742:46"/>
            <p>As the People of God were bid to <hi>flee out of Babylon</hi> of old, <hi>And deliver every man his own Soul,</hi> Jer. 51.6. So in like manner concerning the <hi>Great Babylon,</hi> it's ſaid, <hi>Come out of her my People, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues,</hi> Rev. 18.4.</p>
            <p>The words of the Prophets both <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> concerning <hi>Babylon of Old,</hi> ſeem to reach even to this <hi>Babylon the Great:</hi> So that the <hi>Old Babylon</hi> ſeems to typiſie this very much: as they that read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 50, and 51 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, may perceive. And alſo that they both have a like deſtruction, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.63, 64. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.21. Both are to ſink and not riſe again. This ſhall be the fall of Innovations, and of that power and Dominion that ſtands in them, in the Lord's time. They ſhall ſink in the Waters: in the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:172742:47"/>minds of People, as things born down with great weight. Oh then rejoycing! Joy and gladneſs attends the fall of this <hi>Great Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. Rejoyce over her thou Heaven and the holy Apoſtles, and Prophets for God hath avenged you on her,</hi> Rev. 18.20. What is it that hath done ſo much miſchief to Apoſtles and Prophets, and Saints that God will avenge them thereof, as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and Innovations of men? and therefore they are bid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce when theſe are thrown down like a great Milſtone into the bottom of the deep.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Babylon the Great</hi> ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Inventions and Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men is manifeſt; becauſe it cannot ſtand in any pure Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of God: for then it could not be called <hi>Babylon</hi> nor Confuſion. Therefore it muſt needs ſtand in the Inventions and Innovations of men, deviating
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:172742:47"/>from the pure Diſpenſation of God, or purity of his Truth: and in them <hi>Babylon the Great</hi> will be found. And this will more appear by that which follows. For where the <hi>Great Whore</hi> is found, there <hi>Babylon the Great</hi> muſt be found; it being the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> upon her Forehead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon her Forehead was a name written, Myſtery, Babylon the Great,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore now I come to that thing expreſſed a little afore, namely, That here (<hi>viz.</hi> in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations) we ſhall find the <hi>Great Whore alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What was that, that was ſo much charged upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Old by the Prophets for Whoredom; but that they being a People ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing related to God under the firſt Covenant (or Law) went a whoring after their own Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.39. They did not
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:172742:48"/>keep to the Inſtitutions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of God, but did like the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, or other Nations: they worſhipped Idols, ſet up Groves and Altars of their own <hi>Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and ſuch like: and this was called Whoredom: becauſe it was a breach of their Faithfulneſs, and Loyalty, and Chaſtity to God who had married them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf under a Covenant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.35, 39. <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.30, 37.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe under the Second or New Covenant, if we profeſs our ſelves married to God in Chriſt Jeſus, to walk with him (whom we are commanded to hear and obey) according to his Counſels and Doctrin; and then follow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of our own, and bring in Innovations contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles, this is Spiritual Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom againſt Chriſt. As the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:172742:48"/>of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was whoredom againſt the Marriage Covenant of God given by <hi>Moſes:</hi> So Innovations of Chriſtians is Whoredom againſt the New Covenant given by Chriſt: the Mediator thereof. Theſe two things muſt concur to the making up of the great Whoredom. 1. A Profeſſion of a Marriage Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Chriſt: take him to be our Head, our Guide, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, and Ruler. And then, 2. Great diſloyalty to him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; in rejecting his Counſels, and Spirit; and entertaining and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing a Stranger, <hi>viz.</hi> A Spirit quite contrary to him, and an Enemy to his Counſels; altho profeſſing him, yet introducing and ſetting up Innovations of its own. And whoſoever do out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip or excel others therein, they are the <hi>Great Whore.</hi> And the Spirit of Whoredom will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:172742:49"/>it ſelf moſt among them, by abuſing the Chaſt and Faithful Servants of Chriſt, who love his Precepts, and dare not ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Innovations of men. For the Whoriſh Spirit is a cruel Spirit, hating Chaſtity: becauſe Chaſtity is a check to its Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. I ſpeak of Spiritual Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity and Whoredom.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee what is couched under the Innovations of men. <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Myſtery of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Sodom and Egypt Spiritual, Babylon the Great, and the Great Whore.</hi> Which Innovations moſt abound in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> tho others as yet may not be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether clear of ſome of them.</p>
            <p>But now that I may ſpeak clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and be rightly underſtood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning perſons, I muſt reſume my former diſtinction of perſons: for I now come to ſpeak of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons chiefly. But as I could not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:172742:49"/>well ſpeak of things in an abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſenſe without relation to perſons: ſo now I cannot ſpeak of Perſons without relation to things.</p>
            <p>I look upon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> conſiſting of theſe three Parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Hierarchy, or Ruling Chergy, ſo called.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Inhabitants of the Earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such as in ſincerity of heart ſeek after the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Firſt of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Hierarchy as they ſtand in Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations in the Popedom, or uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Dominion and Exaltation, I take to be the Great Whore: And I ſhall give my reaſons for it, which are theſe two follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the Deſcription of the great Whore, given by the Angel to <hi>John,</hi> doth ſo aptly fit this part of <hi>Rome.</hi> Thoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:172742:50"/>that are given of her, whereby to know her, are found on them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Myſtery ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the great Whores forehead, relates her to the Myſtery of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. And that hath ſuch an exalted one in it as we find only in <hi>Rome,</hi> and no where elſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt of theſe two Reaſons, that the <hi>Great Whores</hi> Deſcription and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters are found in <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, in the Hierarchy thereof the very reading of <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. may give light to any unbyaſſed and indifferent Capacity. I ſhall point out ſeveral of thoſe Characters.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Come hither</hi> (ſaith the Angel to John) <hi>I will ſhew thee the Judgment of the Great Whore that ſitteth upon many Waters, Revel.</hi> 17.1. Here we have one Character of the <hi>Great Whore,</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:172742:50"/>and that is <hi>She ſitteth upon many Waters.</hi> What thoſe Waters are, the Angel expounds to <hi>John</hi> ver. 15. <hi>The Waters which thou ſaweſt, where the Whore ſitteth, are Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Multitudes, and Nations, and Tongues.</hi> She hath a large Dominion, over Peoples, Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Nations and Tongues: a kind of Univerſality; which U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſality they of <hi>Rome</hi> boaſt of, and glory in the Title of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic,</hi> which ſignifies Univerſal; But they are no further Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal than to fulfill this Prophecy. Therefore they glory in that which helps to diſcover their ſhame, giving them one Character of the Great Whore.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>ver.</hi> 2. gives us two more Characters of her. One is, <hi>That the Kings of the Earth have committed fornication with her.</hi> They have been drawn in by her, to go a whoring with her after
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:172742:51"/>her Innovations or Inventions. The other is this: And the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters of the Earth have been made Drunk with the Wine of her fornication. So that here you ſee, there is ſome diſtinction made between the <hi>Great Whore, and thoſe that commit Fornication with her, or are made drunk by her wine.</hi> Which helps to clear my attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Title of the Great Whore, only to their Ruling Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchy. For its they that draw others into the Fornication of their Innovations: others are deluded by them, and made drunk by them. Here be two or three work ſtand need of being opened <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 1. Who are thoſe Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the Earth. To that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey are not the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſation is in Heaven, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> expreſſion is <hi>Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are ſuch as have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Earth: The
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:172742:51"/>Inventions and Innovations of men, are not Heavenly things, but Earthly, ſpringing from the carnal and earthly Wiſdom of mans heart: now theſe having the chief Foundation of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſtanding in the Innovations of men which are earthly, they are the Inhabiters of the Earth. They dwell in the earthly things of mans Wiſdom, not in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things of Gods Wiſdom, grounded in him, and his truth. And therefore, 2ly. Theſe are fit Subjects to be made Drunk with thoſe Innovations, that is, to be inflamed in their Spirits with a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious zeal for them: for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſtands in them: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no marvel if they be violent like Drunken men, againſt all that ſpeak againſt thoſe Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Yea a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ready with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to deſtroy thoſe that will not embrace them. And that eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:172742:52"/>becauſe, 3ly. Thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations are made like wine to them, and therefore called <hi>the Wine of her Fornication.</hi> They ſo agree with the carnal heart of man, that they are as Wine to them: for they nurſe them up in a good conceit of their Condition, indulging their carnal hearts with outward obſervations, and giving them reſt therein, while they are Strangers to God, and to the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of his Spirit. This repoſe in outward things, giving eaſe to, and lulling aſleep their Conſcience is ſweet as Wine to them; and the more, being ſweetned with the words of heavenly things put upon them. By the Artifices uſed about their Innovations, they are ſo taken, that they become ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Drunk, or mad upon them: not more humble, more meek and gentle, and tender-hearted, as the myſtery of Godlineſs makes
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:172742:52"/>men: But theſe become cruelly Drunk, firſt with the Wine of the Fornication of the <hi>Great Whore,</hi> and then together with her, drunk with blood, being made hands fit for her to deſtroy with. Which ſhews what Spirit is at work un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Innovations.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I would here advertiſe the Reader, that I do not look upon all that are counted of their Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archy to be equally concerned, or have an equal ſhare in this great Whoredom; tho I cannot excuſe them. For ſome may be more paſſive, and carryed along with the ſtream and ſtrength of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part, who are fierce and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and are the chief enforcers of their Innovations. As when the Prohibition of Marriage was impoſed upon their Clergy, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them did greatly withſtand it to their power; but were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:172742:53"/>to it by the greater power of the over-ruling part, and made to ſubmit to it againſt their minds. Such I look upon rather as Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives than otherwiſe. And ſo the caſe may be with many in other Innovations.</p>
            <p>But to proceed in the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Characters of the great Whore: the Angel took <hi>John</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Wilderneſs, in the Spirit, that there he might ſee her more fully. Not that the great Whore is in the Wilderneſs, who ſits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many Waters, Peoples mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes Tongues: but that inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates that ſuch as are led out from her by the Spirit into a ſolitary Wilderneſs condition, ſhall beſt ſee her. And indeed they ſhall beſt ſee the Innovations of leſſer Whores, who are not in the Whoredom, or involved in the Innovations.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:172742:53"/>
            <p>Now what did <hi>John</hi> ſee? <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Woman ſit upon a ſcarlet coloured Beaſt, full of Names of Blaſphemy, having ſeven heads and ten Horns.</hi> Here ſhe is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by that which ſupports her, and over which ſhe ruleth, as one rules over the Beaſt they ſit upon. The Great Whore is a pompous Whore, and ſits upon a pompous Beaſt, a ſcarlet coloured Beaſt: that is, an earthly pompous Power; not upon the power of the Spirit, by which the Apoſtles of Chriſt were ſupported, but upon an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power, full of blaſphemous names againſt the true power, and the faithful ſervants of Chriſt, who abhor the Innovations of men. This is a Beaſt ſutable to the great Whore, and of one Spirit with her; and fortified to uphold her in her large Dominion over Peoples, Multitudes, Nations and Tongues: having ſeven Heads,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:172742:54"/>and ten Horns, and what thoſe are the Angel unfolds afterwards.</p>
            <p>To go on with the Characters of the Woman, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>And the Woman was arrayed in Purple, and ſcarlet colour, and decked with Gold, and precious Stones, and Pearls; having a Golded Cup in her hand, full of abominations and filthineſs of her Fornication.</hi> Here ſhe is deſcribed by her <hi>Ornaments,</hi> and by her <hi>Cup</hi> which contains her Fornication. Her <hi>Ornaments</hi> are ſuch as are uſed by Kings and Potentates of the World, Purple and Scarlet, and Gold, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, not ſuch Ornaments as the Apoſtles were adorned with, and approved of in the Saints; ſuch as <hi>Humility, Meekneſs, Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Sincerity, Truth,</hi> and ſuch as the Goſpel approves of: but ſuch Ornaments as might make her of equal Splendour with the Princes of the World, if not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:172742:54"/>above them. Doth not the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy of <hi>Rome</hi> anſwer this mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence?</p>
            <p>And then ſhe is deſcribed by her <hi>Cup in her hand</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the <hi>filthineſs of her Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> This demonſtrates that her Fornication is Spiritual: being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a Cup carried in the hand: and that is, the model of her Worſhip, or compoſure of her Service, which contains her ſpiritual Fornication: and going a whoring after her own inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This <hi>Cup</hi> is a very remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Character. 1. It's call'd a <hi>Cup,</hi> becauſe it contains her Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and alſo becauſe out of it ſhe pours forth the Wine of her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication to the inhabiters of the Earth, wherewith ſhe makes them drunk: It contains their Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after which they go a whoring. 2. This <hi>Cup</hi> is a Golden <hi>Cup.</hi> It's golden to outward appearance.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:172742:55"/>Their Outward appearances of Worſhip are not only glorious to the outward eye, being perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great Ceremony, coſt and ſplendour: but alſo the minds and ears of carnal earthly ſpirits are dazed with the ſeraphical expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and golden words uſed therein. 3. This <hi>Cup</hi> is in her hand. In whoſe hand? In the great Whores hand: This ſhews that they that hand this <hi>Cup</hi> to the People, they are the great Whore. It's in the Womans hand, the great Whores hand. It's framed alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and beautified with all the art they can, and carried in the hand. It's already formed, to be put into the hand of every Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor that is devoted to their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations. Their Worſhip is not carried in the heart, and ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Spirit of God, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred from his Gift, to the comfort and edification of people,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:172742:55"/>as their Worſhip did in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles daies: but this is in the hand, and any wicked perſon can admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter it, or hand it forth. 4 It's full of abominations and filthineſs of her Fornication. It's full of Innovations and Inventions of men: which are an abomination to God. And to go after them, is to go a whoring from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did. <hi>They went a Whoring after their own Inventions,</hi> Pſal. 106.39.</p>
            <p>Next, we come to the <hi>Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Forehead</hi> of the great Whore, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. which Couples all theſe together, <hi>viz. The great Whore, The Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> and <hi>Babylon the Great.</hi> So that, find one, and you find them all. The Inſcription is this, <hi>Myſtery, Babylon the Great, the Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the Earth.</hi> This being writ upon the forehead of the great Whore,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:172742:56"/>ſhews that ſhe is all this, in her all this is found: this being as her Crime writ upon her Forehead: or a proper name extant to know her by. Now if you can find out the Myſtery of Iniquity by him that <hi>Heads</hi> it, that ſits in the Temple of God (the Church) exalted above all Magiſtrates; then you have the great Whore alſo. Or if you can find the great Whore by the Characters given of her, then you have the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity, and <hi>Babylon</hi> the Great: for they are all co-inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, being concatinated in one Chain, as the inſcription on the great Whores Forehead ſhews plainly.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Words Myſtery, and Babylon the Great;</hi> ſeeing I have ſpoken of them before, I refer to that; and ſo paſs on to the next Character of the great Whore, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>And I ſaw the Woman drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:172742:56"/>with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus: and when I ſaw her, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred with great admiration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's a mark of a bloody die, which the great Whore can never wipe off. But the more ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to blot it out, by deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe that ſee her guiltineſs, the deeper ſhe ſets it, and the larger ſhe makes it. Here every one may ſee, that the great Whore is a <hi>bloody</hi> Whore. She's drunken with Blood: which ſignificantly expreſſes her great thirſt after the blood of thoſe ſhe kills: ſo that ſhe ſwallows down their blood greedily, without remorſe, and without all reaſon, ſaving that they withſtand her Innovations. Where ſhall we find this bloody drunkenneſs, ſo much, as in the bloody raging Maſſacres, Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Cruelties which have been acted under the dominion
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:172742:57"/>and power of <hi>Rome;</hi> and of thoſe who have been infected with her innovations? None like thoſe. And that which heightens this wickedneſs, is, that ſhe is drunk with the Blood of Saints <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is of holy men, innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are of a Righteous life, and good converſation, and truly fear the Lord. Who are alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Martyrs or witneſſes of Jeſus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, ſuch as bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Jeſus, acknowledging and owning him and his Doctrine, and willing to loſe their lives; rather than to deny the truth delivered to us by him, and his Servants. Such as theſe ſhe kills, becauſe they ſee her innovations, and cannot ſtoop to them. That's greatly remarkable alſo, that her bloody drunkenneſs is ſuch, as put <hi>John</hi> to admiration. <hi>John</hi> lived in times of Perſecution, and ſaw cruelty enough no doubt, being
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:172742:57"/>baniſhed into the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Patmos</hi> at that time: But that was not it that put <hi>John</hi> to an aſtoniſhment (as ſome would have it.) But it was ſomething that was to come to paſs afterwards, as the Angel ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.2. <hi>I will ſhew the things which muſt be hereafter.</hi> To ſhew <hi>John</hi> a Church (under the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of a Woman) ſo far to go a Whoring from Chriſt after her own inventions, that ſhe did not ſpare his moſt precious Servants, nor any that adhered to them? but ſhed their Blood in abundance for the ſake of her inventions, and innovations, and yet profeſſed her ſelf to be the Spouſe, yea, the only Spouſe and Church of Chriſt: <hi>I</hi> ſay, to ſee one ſo highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſt, and yet acting ſo highly contrary to hisnature, and deſtroying his Servants, this might indeed make <hi>John</hi> greatly to wonder with great admiration.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:172742:58"/>But the tyranny of thoſe preſent times that <hi>John</hi> lived in, under the perſecuting heathen Emperors, could be no ſuch admiration to him. For its no great admiration to ſee a known Enemy ſhed the blood of thoſe he is againſt. But to profeſs the higheſt Loyalty to Chriſt, and commit the greateſt Cruelty againſt his Children and People, this might put one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment. <hi>O Rome! Rome!</hi> O backſliding <hi>Rome!</hi> Who could make <hi>John</hi> aſtoniſhed but thee! Who once was a pure Church: but to ſee thee profeſs the ſame Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus or Saviour as formerly, and be ſo cruelly hard-hearted as to devour the tender Lambs of Jeſus, who will rather dye than betray his Doctrine; and alſo to devour them ſo abundantly; who would not be aſtoniſhed at ſuch a dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy! O repent, repent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore miſery come upon thee.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:172742:58"/>
            <p>Another Character of the great Whore followeth <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.7. and 18. <hi>verſes. And the Angel ſaid unto me, wherefore didſt thou mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel? I will tell the Myſtery of the Woman, and of the beaſt that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth her,</hi> ver. 18. <hi>The Woman which thou ſaweſt is that great City which Reigneth over the Kings of the Earth.</hi> Or nearer the Greek words thus, <hi>which hath a Kingdom above the Kings of the Earth:</hi> for the words of the Greek are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Theſe words being the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Myſtery of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; make it plain, that by Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is underſtood, <hi>That great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which hath a Kingdom above the Kings of the Earth.</hi> Now where ſhall we find ſuch a City beſides <hi>Rome,</hi> that hath in it ſuch a Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, in which all theſe Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of the great Whore are found?
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:172742:59"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> hath a Kingdom above the Kings of the Earth. And the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of iniquity may ſay the ſame? ſhe hath one in it, exalted above all, called God, above all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. So that you may clearly ſee That this great Whore, and the Myſtery of iniquity fall in one with the other: find the one, and you may find the other.</p>
            <p>This great Whore, this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, this great City, is terrible to the Kings of the Earth, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Kingdom above them. For She can ſtrike them with her thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bolts at her pleaſure, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne them, by moving the Waves of the Sea againſt them, againſt which there is no with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. To ſpeak plainer, She can make them an execration with her Anathema; and then raiſe the Waves of the people againſt them which they cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: and then Surrogate others
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:172742:59"/>to take their Throne. Is not this to have a Kingdom above them? Yea ſo great a Dominion ſhe hath over them, that ſhe can make them buckle to her pleaſure, and wait at her gates, to humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at her Feet, as not worthy to kiſs her hands. This is to bring them lower, then a King brings his Subjects. For he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits his Subjects to kiſs his hand: But the diſtance between this great Whore and Emperors is ſo great, that its enough for them to kiſs her Feet.</p>
            <p>Such power hath this great Whore had as to cauſe the Son to riſe againſt his Father, to turn him out of his Throne. <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, the Son of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, when his Father was ſtruck with the Thunderbolt of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Pope <hi>Paſchalis</hi> 2. and ejected from being Emperor; he roſe up againſt his Father, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:172742:60"/>put him in Priſon, where with grief of mind he died. And this <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth his Son declared, that he did not thus perſecute his Father out of a deſire to Reign; but <hi>(Studio obedientia erga ſedem Apoſtolicam)</hi> out of a zealous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Apoſtolick Seat, (for ſuch titles the great Whore hath arrogated to her ſelf.) This was done about the beginning of the 12th. Century. And in the 13th. Century Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third. <hi>Othonem Anathemate ferit, Imperium ei abrogat, omneſque ab ejus obedientia &amp; fide abſolvit.</hi> He Anathematized <hi>Otho,</hi> deprived him of the Empire, and abſolved all perſons from their obedience and fidelity to him. And in Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury 14. Hiſtory tells us of <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> 8. that he writ, <hi>ſe effe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in temporalibus &amp; Spirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in univer ſo mundo,</hi> that is, that he was Lord both in Temporals
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:172742:60"/>and Spirituals in the whole World. And after his Death it was ſaid of him, <hi>Hoc modo (ſc. moe rore animi) mortuus eſt Bonifacius ille qui Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoribus, Regibus, Principibus, Nationibus, Populis terrorem potius quam religionem injicere conabatur: quique dare regna &amp; auferre, pelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re homines ac reducere pro arbitrio animi conabatur. Platin.</hi> Thus (that is, with grief of mind) dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>Boniface</hi> who made it his buſineſs to imprint terror upon the hearts of Emperors and Kings, &amp;c. Rather than Religion: and who endeavoured to <hi>give</hi> and <hi>take away Kingdoms, to baniſh and call home,</hi> at his pleaſure. But the height and Dominion of this great Whore or Popedom is ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that I need not inſiſt further upon it.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what a one the great Whore is: and how like to her the Popedom is, ſitting upon
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:172742:61"/>many Waters, <hi>i.e.</hi> Peoples, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, Tongues, Nations; draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kings of the Earth to commit Fornication with her, proſtrating themſelves to her Innovations, or Whoredoms; making alſo the Inhabiters of the earth Drunk with the pleaſantneſs of her Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Innovations; born up with great power; living in great pomp; carrying the filthineſs of her Fornication in her hand, in a golden Cup, very taking to the carnal mind; and bearing upon her Forehead Myſtery, thats her name in part, ſhewing her affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Myſtery of Iniquity; one alſo that makes her ſelf drunk with the plenty of blood of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent people; and one that hath a Kingdom above the Kings of the Earth. Theſe are enough to know her by.</p>
            <p>But the Angel ſtill goes further, to make her more fully known
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:172742:61"/>by other things appertaining to the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that carries her, which is deſcribed by his ſeven Heads, and ten Horns. His Heads were ſeven Hills, and alſo ſeven Kings or Governments. His Horns were ten Kings.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only take notice of that here which is eaſie for any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Capacity to underſtand; and add that to the foregoing marks of the great Whore. And by this we may underſtand the very place where ſhe is chiefly to be found.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſeven Heads</hi> (ſaid the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel) <hi>are ſeven Mountains on which the Woman ſitteth:</hi> This is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the ſeven Heads, <hi>She ſits upon ſeven Hills.</hi> Now it's well known that <hi>Rome</hi> is ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated on ſeven Hills or Mountains. And therefore was known by the name <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs ſepticollis,</hi> and <hi>Septi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which words
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:172742:62"/>ſignifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeven Hills, or ſeven Heads. That's one Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or unfolding of the ſeven Heads of the Beaſt that carries the great Whore. The Angel alſo gives another interpretation of thoſe ſeven Heads: that both meeting together, they might make the more certain diſcovery of her. That ſecond interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not then at that time whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfilled, when the Angel gave it: And that ſtill adds more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and certainty to the applying of it to <hi>Rome.</hi> The interpretat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is this, <hi>And there are ſeven Kings, five are fallen, and one is, and the other is not yet come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and when he cometh he muſt continue a while.</hi> Theſe ſeven Kings are: rightly taken by prudent under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding men, to be the ſeven Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments that <hi>Rome</hi> hath had, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Kings,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls;</hi> thirdly, <hi>Dictators;</hi> fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:172742:62"/>
               <hi>Decemviri;</hi> fifthly, <hi>Tribunes</hi> Which five were fallen in <hi>John</hi>'s time: then <hi>One is,</hi> ſaid the Angel to <hi>John,</hi> and that was the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> which made the <hi>Sixth,</hi> and was ſtanding in <hi>John</hi>'s time. But the other, the <hi>Seventh,</hi> which was the <hi>Popes,</hi> is not yet come ſaid he. And when he is come, he muſt continue a while.</p>
            <p>How aptly do theſe things fit <hi>Rome,</hi> even as a garment fitted to ones back. So that finding all theſe Characters of the great Whore ſo apparently in <hi>Rome,</hi> how can ſhe clear her ſelf from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that very great Whore?</p>
            <p>Only this I would have the Reader to mind, that by <hi>Rome</hi> here I do not underſtand every individual perſon in her; but the Ruling Hierarchical power of <hi>Rome,</hi> which makes the carnal and earthly people drunk with the Wine of her Fornication, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:172742:63"/>holds the People of God in Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity under her. As <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> was charged with Whoredom in like caſe of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own inventions, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all in it were not guilty: but God had a precious people in it, who were grieved therewith. So it may be with <hi>Rome.</hi> And ſo by Pope, I do not ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand every individual Pope, as the Myſtery and the power of the Popedom in which they ſtand.</p>
            <p>I now paſs on from the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Rome</hi> to the Inhabiters of the Earth, who are a People ſet on miſchief by the Whoredomes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the great Whore. Theſe are a People ſo intoxicated with the Wine of her Fornication (that is with the Innovations of the great Whore) that like drunken men they are full of quarrel, heady bold out-facers of Truth, haters of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:172742:63"/>all that ſtands in the way of their Innovations, and ready with ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger minds to embrew their hands in the blood of righteous people, if their Maſters do but call them Hereticks, and ſet them on; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho they have no other provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or reaſon to do it, but only becauſe they are againſt their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations. Theſe are very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, ſo that the great Whore wants not hands to execute her fury upon the innocent Servants of Chriſt, when ſhe ſees a fit time to employ them: And this they are ready to do in loyalty to her Uſurped Authority. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore altho they are not guiltleſs, yet ſhe is chiefly charged with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunk with the blood of the Servants of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> As <hi>David</hi> was charged with the blood of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> becauſe it proceeded from him: So the great Whore ſtandsguilty of all the blood ſhed in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:172742:64"/>and loyalty to her Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But in a dangerous thing to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the hand of there that ſight againſt God, and againſt'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſimplicity and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of his wares, and innocency and fidelity of his Servants. It may go eaſier with thoſe that are drunk with the Wine of the great. Whores Fornication, than which her that is drunk with blood but I think none that underſtands the danger, would be in <hi>Sodoms</hi> uſe, becauſe it ſhall be more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for them, than for ſome other Cities at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>There is a third ſort of People under the Dominion of the great. Whore, whom my Soul longs after; whoſe Spirits are drawn after the Lord, and who truly fear him; altho their underſtandings may be captivated under many of her Innovations. Theſe when
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:172742:64"/>they come to ſee their liberty in the Lord, may ſay with the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, O Lord our God, other Lords beſides thee have had dominion, over us: but by thee only will we made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy name,</hi> Iſa. 26, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Other Lord have had dominion over ye, to cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to make mention of thy Name in their ſuperſtations waies: but by thee only, even by thy ſelf, and thy direction and aſſiſtance will we now henceforth make mention of thy Name.</hi> They that have been in bondage under enforced Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, when they are made right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of it, will ſee the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion that other Lords have had over them, will not ſatisfie; but there will be a cry in their hearts, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord alone may rule over their Conſcience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that all their profeſſion of him, or making mention of his name, may proceed from himſelf: and ſo ſhall they worſhip him in Spirit
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:172742:65"/>and in truth. Theſe may ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, <hi>By the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Babylon there we ſat down, yea we wept when we remembred Zion, Pſal.</hi> 137.1. I know whoſe caſe that hath been under leſſer Innovations. The heart that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fears the Lord, and pants after him, longs after the purity of his ways: and when it gets a glimpſe thereof, ſits down weeping under all other bondages of humane tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Innovations, finding it ſelf as it were in a Captivity, or baniſhment from its own Land, which it longs to be at; and that is the enjoyment of the prefence of the Lord, in the purity and ſimplicity of his ways.</p>
            <p>Now my Soul and Spirit ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathizes with ſuch as theſe, breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lord for their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, whereſoever they are, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had a fellow-feeling of their Bondage; and I hope deliverance
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:172742:65"/>draws nigh to many. For what is their Captivity, but their Thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Bondage under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations of men? And what ſhall be their deliverance, but the falling of thoſe Innovations which hold them Captive, and their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet in the liberty of the Spirit. Though men have built a Tower of their own Inventions, whoſe top may reach to Heaven, and upon the top of which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſet men into Heaven; yet down again this muſt tumble. This <hi>Babel,</hi> this Great Whore, this Myſtery of Iniquity, this Mother of Harlots muſt have a fall: and then that Voice will call to them from Heaven. <hi>Come out of her my People that ye be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of her Sins, and that ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not of her Plagues, Rev.</hi> 18.4. Now what ſhall be this great fall of <hi>Babylon?</hi> I anſwer, if we conſider what was the fall of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:172742:66"/>
               <hi>Jews,</hi> we may partly underſtand thereby what ſhall be the fall of <hi>Babylon.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> fall was their continuing in that which God by Chriſt Jeſus came to put an end to. They fell ſhort of the Grace and Glory that was revealed and came by Jeſus Chriſt, altho they continue a People ſtill. So <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> the Houſe of Captivity ſhall fall: Innovations or Inventions of men after which they have gone a Whoring, and under which the Seed of God hath been held in great bondage, theſe ſhall have thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the hearts of men; they ſhall underſtandingly ſee them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hated of the Lord, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Spirit of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Truth revealed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and witneſſed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> being ſeen and fallen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, they ſhall
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:172742:66"/>ſtrongly be called out of them them by the Spirit of God. For obſerve, after it is ſaid <hi>Babylon the Great is fallen, is fallen,</hi> that Voice is uttered, <hi>Come out of her my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> For after the great fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> there ſhall yet be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in or upholding of her Innovations by ſome. But Gods people are called out: they that fear God and love his truth ſhall be called out; and ſo the reſt that remain in them, ſhall be captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed themſelves thereby, as a Bird in a Cage. For thoſe Inventions and Innovations of men ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Habitation of Devils, and a hold of every foul Spirit, and a Cage of every unclean and hatefull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> and that after <hi>Babylons</hi> great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.2.</p>
            <p>This fall of <hi>Baylon</hi> the Great that is, the fall of mens Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall be no ſmall matter: for it will carry along with it Plagues
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:172742:67"/>and Death, and Famine, and Mourning. The Scarlet coloured Whore, that hath been decked with Gold, and precious Stones, and Pearls, anp lived deliciouſly, and Reigned in great Pomp, by by the Merchandize of her Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, ſhe ſhall have torment and ſorrow, and be pinched of her Deliciouſneſs, when men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſee the cheat of her Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, and will buy it no more, when they begin to ſee the Vanity and wickedneſs of her Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and will no more buy any of them; then comes her Plagues and Torment, and Sorrow, and Famine, and Mourning. For what is it that hath upheld the Great Whore, but the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of her Innovations? And theſe things men ſhall come to ſee, and Kings ſhall ſee. And when they ſee it, they ſhall hate the Whore, and make her Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and Naked, and ſhall Eat her
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:172742:67"/>Fleſh, and burn her with Fire. Her Innovations are as her very Fleſh and Blood, which give her Comelineſs and Vigour: if you conſume them you put her to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and even eat her Fleſh, as it were, and burn her with Fire: and this even thoſe Kings ſhall do who have given their power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Beaſt that carries her, and whom ſhe hath drawn in to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Fornication with her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16, 17.</p>
            <p>And bleſſed be God who hath put it into the hearts of ſome Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Earth, to make void one great Innovation of the Myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of Iniquity, for the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods people, that is, to oppoſe that perſecuting of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for Conſcience ſake, or worſhipping God according to their Conſcience. This is a great ſtep of Reformation; and the King of Kings make them ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full therein, and bleſs their good
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:172742:68"/>Endeavours: and open their eyes yet further, and the eyes of all that are honeſt hearted, to ſee ſtill further and further into the Myſteries of his Kingdom, and to embrace them; and alſo into the Myſteries of Iniquity, to turn from them.</p>
            <p>Oh! What rejoycing will there be in the Earth, among all that fear God and love his truth, when the Inventions and Innovations of men are caſt out, and the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the Goſpel ſhall be free for all men to walk in! When thoſe Innovations of men that have cauſed ſo much bloodſhed, ſhall come to an end, and like a great Milſtone ſhall be caſt into the Sea, and be found no more, then will follow the Marriage of the Bride, the Lambs Wife; and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. For the Lord God om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent ſigneth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6, 7.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:172742:68"/>
            <head>A <hi>POST-SCRIPT,</hi> to thoſe that are Members or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pholders of the Great Whore.</head>
            <p>THE Lord ſeeks not the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of people, but that they ſhou'd repent of the evil of their ways and be preſerved: and that's the deſire of him who hath writ theſe things. Therefore his advice to them that find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves included in humane Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations is this, to humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the mighty hand of God, and lay down what they find to be contrary to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; left they ſuffer in upholding
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:172742:69"/>that which God will conſume and deſtroy. For tho ſingle perſons cannot reform the degenerated State of things, yet they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves. The Pope may reform himſelf; a Cardinal may reform himſelf, by withdrawing himſelf from that he ſees evil, and in humility of Spirit ſubmitting himſelf to the Counſels of God, and ſimplicity of the Goſpel, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide the Innovations of men. The Lords pleaſure is, that man ſhould rather be preſerved than deſtroyed. <hi>I wrold have healed Babylon,</hi> (ſaith he:) Then if ſhe be not healed, where lies the fault? Is not her Deſtruction of her ſelf? Oh! that you could ſee the evils that are introduced into the profeſſion of Chriſtianity by the Wiſdom of men, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the World and the Glory thereof, and exaltation in the Earth, in compariſon of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:172742:69"/>Crown of Glory which fadeth not as Earthly glory doth! How much better a purchaſe would you obtain, than the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fading tranſitory momentany glory of this world! And no man hath run himſelf ſo far from the Lord, but that there may be a returning, except he deny the Lord that bought him. They that were the greateſt Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> were adviſed to repent; and threatned if they did not: which implies that the mercies of God were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receive them, if they did repent. O return, return to the purity and ſimplicity of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as it was in the Primitive times of the Apoſtles: and lay aſide all theſe ſeparating Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Innovations of men, which divide between Chriſtians and Chriſtians; that we may come into Unity as at the firſt. What!
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:172742:70"/>is Chriſt divided? No certainly, he is One, and his Doctrine is One. Its the Device and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of men that divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. O what Acclamati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w will there be among all that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in truth, when the ſeparating Inventions and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of man are caſt forth! <hi>This is the great fall of Babylon over which the Saints and Servants of God ſhall ſing Alelujah.</hi> But the Spirit of God ſeems to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that ſhe will not be healed, ſaying of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> of old, <hi>we would have hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Babylon, but ſhe is not healed.</hi> And I think there is little ground to expect that ſo great a Society of men, ſo ſtrongly conjoyned in a Myſtery of Innovations, can make a publique Reformation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together; becauſe its moſt likely that the greater number of them will be for maintaining their
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:172742:70"/>earthly Intereſt, and worldly Glory, that they have in their Kingdom of Innovations: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord calls to particular perſons to withdraw, ſaying, <hi>Come out of her my People, that ye be not partakers of her Sins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues, Rev.</hi> 18.4. For let her be as ſtrong as ſhe can, yet ſhe hath to deal with one that is ſtronger. <hi>Strong is the Lord God who judgeth her;</hi> ſo that ſhe cannot avoid his Stroke. Therefore let all that fear the Lord come out of her; come out of the Inventions, Innovations, or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men, into the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and ſincerity of truth, where you ſhall find the Comfortable preſence and power of the Lord going before you, and as a Lamp enlightning your paths, that you may follow him in ſafety, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to your Souls, as he leads and goes before you.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:172742:71"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172742:71"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed and Sold by</hi> Thomas Northcott, <hi>in</hi> George-Yard, <hi>in</hi> Lumbard-ſtreet.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>ISaac Penington</hi>'s works, price 12. <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Samuel Fiſher</hi>'s Works, price 12 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Francis Howgil</hi>'s Works, price 10 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Barclay</hi>'s Apology for the true Chriſtian Divinity, as the ſame is held forth and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the People called in ſcorn Quakers, price 4 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Foxe</hi>'s <hi>New-England</hi> Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand quenched, price 4 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:172742:72"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hugh Cloaks</hi> Call from Sin to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Life, pric. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of the Suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rings of <hi>Thomas Briggs.</hi> 4 <hi>d.</hi> ½.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oex's</hi> Teſtimony to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere of Ships and Seamen, 1 <hi>d.</hi> ½.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Laythes</hi> Excreiſe of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it in Spiritual things,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>James Parke</hi>'s Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> to Friends, 1 <hi>d.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Sand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>and</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>piſtles of Love, 2 <hi>d.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>A Journal of the Travels of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Caton,</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Pen</hi>'s no Croſs no Crown, 2 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Keith</hi>'s Immediate Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, 2 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Divine immediate Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, 1 <hi>s.</hi> 2. <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His way to the City of God deſcribed, 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:172742:72"/>
               <item>—His Fundamental Truths of Chriſtianity, 8 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Trow Chriſt owned, 4 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Rector Corrected, 8 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Truths Defence, 10 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>E. Bathurſt</hi>'s Vindication of Truth, 8 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Shewen</hi>'s True Chriſtians Faith and Experience, 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Steghen Criſp</hi>'s Epiſtle to Friends concerning preſentand ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Times, 2 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Barclay</hi>'s Epiſtle of Love, 2 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Poſſibility and neceſſity of inward and immediate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valation, 3 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Carechiſm and Conſeffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, 9 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:172742:73"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Field</hi>'s, and <hi>Richard Scoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi>'s Friendly Advice in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Twelves.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Foxe</hi>'s Inſtructions for Reading, Writing of true Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gramatiſta,</hi> or the young Grama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, being a very uſeful Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Book for Children, to which is added the form of Bills, Bonds and Indentures, 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alſo Bibles of ſeveral ſorts, and Teſtaments, and many other ſorts of Books.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:172742:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
